♪ ♪
♪ ♪
MADAME MORRIBLE (amplified): Citizens of Oz,
मैडम मॉरिबल (विस्तारित): ओज़ के नागरिक,
there have been 12 tide turns
अब तक 12 बार ज्वार-भाटे की दिशा बदल चुकी है
since the Wicked Witch of the West escaped
पश्चिम की दुष्ट चुड़ैल के भाग जाने के बाद से
with our Grimmerie.
हमारी ग्रिमेरी के साथ।
Shield your children.
अपने बच्चों की रक्षा करें।
Trust no animals.
किसी भी जानवर पर भरोसा न करें।
She will be eliminated.
उसे बाहर कर दिया जाएगा।
(thunder crashes)
(बिजली कड़कती है)
Until then, the Wizard's vision
तब तक, जादूगर की दृष्टि
for the Oz of tomorrow marches on.
कल के ओज़ के लिए आगे बढ़ रहा है।
(animal grumbles)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
GUARD 1: Do it! Move!
गार्ड 1: करो! आगे बढ़ो!
(bellows)
(धौंकनी)
All right, load it up.
ठीक है, इसे लोड करो।
Come on! Let's go! Move!
चलो! चलें! जल्दी करो!
GUARD 2: No speaking.
गार्ड 2: बोलना मना है।
The Wizard needs the road finished.
जादूगर को सड़क का काम पूरा करवाना है।
(chatter continues)
(बातचीत जारी है)
-(steam hissing) -(mechanical creaking)
(भाप की सरसराहट) (यांत्रिक चरमराहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
-(animals grumbling) -GUARD 3: Move! Move!
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट) - रक्षक 3: हटो! हटो!
GUARD 1: Come on, let's go! Move!
गार्ड 1: चलो, चलते हैं! जल्दी करो!
GUARD 4: Fill up that basket!
गार्ड 4: उस टोकरी को भर दो!
-Keep moving. -(animal whimpers)
चलते रहो। (जानवर की धीमी आवाज़)
Come on.
चलो भी।
(animals grumbling)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
Come on. Keep moving.
चलो, चलते रहो।
(grunts) Get up!
(घुरघुराहट) उठो!
(animal wailing)
(जानवरों का विलाप)
-Come on. (grunts) -(animal groaning)
चलो। (घुरघुराहट) (जानवर की कराह)
(whoosh)
(तेज़ आवाज़)
(grumbling)
(बड़बड़ाते हुए)
Whoa. Settle down.
अरे वाह! शांत हो जाओ।
-(bellowing) -(gasps)
(चीखते हुए) (सांस फूलना)
Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa.
वाह, वाह, वाह, वाह, वाह, वाह।
Get back! (gasps)
पीछे हटो! (हैरान होकर)
Retreat! Guards, retreat!
पीछे हटो! रक्षकों, पीछे हटो!
It's the Witch!
ये तो चुड़ैल है!
(screams, grunts)
(चीखें, कराहें)
(screams)
(चीखें)
(grunting)
(घुरघुराहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(panting)
(हाँफते हुए)
(monkeys screeching in distance)
( दूर से बंदरों की चीखने की आवाज)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(sonic boom)
(ध्वनि बूम)
(panting)
(हाँफते हुए)
The Witch! She's back!
चुड़ैल! वो वापस आ गई है!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
OZIANS: ♪ Every day, more Wicked ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ हर दिन, और भी ज़्यादा दुष्ट ♪
♪ Every day, the terror grows ♪
♪ हर दिन, आतंक बढ़ता जा रहा है ♪
♪ All of Oz is ever on alert ♪
♪ ऑस्ट्रेलिया में हर समय सतर्कता बरती जाती है ♪
♪ That's the way with Wicked ♪
♪ दुष्टों का यही तरीका है ♪
♪ Spreading fear where'er she goes ♪
♪ वो जहाँ भी जाती है, डर फैलाती है ♪
♪ Seeking out new victims she can hurt ♪
♪ नए शिकारों की तलाश में जिन्हें वह नुकसान पहुंचा सके ♪
MADAME MORRIBLE: ♪ Like some terrible green blizzard ♪
मैडम मॉरिबल: ♪ किसी भयानक हरे बर्फीले तूफान की तरह ♪
♪ Throughout the land, she flies ♪
♪ वह पूरे देश में उड़ती है ♪
♪ Defaming our poor Wizard ♪
♪ हमारे बेचारे जादूगर को बदनाम करना ♪
♪ With her calumnies and lies ♪
♪ उसके झूठे आरोपों और झूठों के साथ ♪
-OZIANS: ♪ She lies ♪ -(monkeys screeching)
-ओज़ियंस: ♪ वह झूठ बोलती है ♪ -(बंदरों की चीख)
♪ She lies ♪
♪ वह झूठ बोलती है ♪
(Ozians vocalizing)
(ओज़ियन लोग आवाज़ निकाल रहे हैं)
Go, go!
जाओ, जाओ!
GUARD: Release them!
गार्ड: इन्हें छोड़ दो!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Save us from the Wicked ♪
♪ हमें दुष्टों से बचाओ ♪
♪ Shield us so we won't be hexed ♪
♪ हमारी रक्षा करो ताकि हम पर जादू-टोना न हो ♪
♪ Give us warning: Where will she strike next? ♪
♪ हमें चेतावनी दीजिए: वह अगला हमला कहाँ करेगी? ♪
♪ Where will she strike next? ♪
♪ अब वो अगला हमला कहाँ करेगी? ♪
♪ Where will she strike ♪
♪ वह कहाँ प्रहार करेगी ♪
♪ Next? ♪
♪ अगला? ♪
♪ When I stop the Wizard ♪
♪ जब मैं जादूगर को रोक देता हूँ ♪
♪ All Oz will applaud ♪
♪ सारा ऑस्ट्रेलिया तालियाँ बजाएगा ♪
♪ How I saved them from the Wizard ♪
♪ मैंने उन्हें जादूगर से कैसे बचाया ♪
♪ By revealing he's a fraud ♪
♪ उसके धोखेबाज होने का खुलासा करके ♪
♪ If I can just make them believe in the truth ♪
♪ अगर मैं उन्हें सच्चाई पर विश्वास दिला सकूँ ♪
♪ That all that he says is a lie ♪
♪ उसकी सारी बातें झूठ हैं ♪
♪ That's when they'll finally bid ♪
♪ तभी वे अंततः बोली लगाएंगे ♪
♪ The Wizard goodbye ♪
♪ जादूगर का अलविदा ♪
ELPHABA: Come with me.
एल्फाबा: मेरे साथ आओ।
GLINDA: What?
ग्लिंडा: क्या?
ELPHABA: To meet the Wizard.
एल्फाबा: जादूगर से मिलने के लिए।
PALACE GUARD: The Wizard will see you now.
महल का रक्षक: अब जादूगर आपसे मिलेंगे।
(train chugging, whistle blows)
(ट्रेन के चलने की आवाज़, सीटी बजती है)
♪ Dearest Glinda, you are still the best ♪
♪ मेरी प्यारी ग्लिंडा, तुम अब भी सबसे अच्छी हो ♪
Well, I guess.
ठीक है, मुझे लगता है।
♪ Others are Good, but you're the Goodliest ♪
♪ दूसरे अच्छे हैं, लेकिन तुम सबसे अच्छे हो ♪
♪ We feel merry, we feel cheery ♪
♪ हमें खुशी महसूस हो रही है, हम प्रसन्न हैं ♪
♪ Just to gaze on your reflection ♪
♪ बस तुम्हारी परछाई को निहारने के लिए ♪
♪ Only you disprove the theory ♪
♪ केवल आप ही इस सिद्धांत को गलत साबित कर सकते हैं ♪
-♪ That you can't improve perfection ♪ -(sighs)
-♪ कि पूर्णता को बेहतर नहीं बनाया जा सकता ♪ -(आह भरते हुए)
Thank you.
धन्यवाद।
Good. Good. Good. Good. Good.
अच्छा। अच्छा। अच्छा। अच्छा। अच्छा।
Good.
अच्छा।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
(students gasp)
(छात्र चौंक जाते हैं)
She's so Good.
वह बहुत अच्छी है।
-(murmurs of agreement) -(Ozians cheering)
(सहमति की फुसफुसाहट) (ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
OZIAN ANNOUNCER (amplified): Glinda the Good.
ओज़ियन उद्घोषक (प्रबलित): ग्लिंडा द गुड।
-♪ La, la ♪ -(cheering continues)
-♪ ला, ला ♪ -(जयकार जारी है)
♪ La, la ♪
♪ ला, ला ♪
♪ La, la, la, la ♪
♪ ला, ला, ला, ला ♪
-♪ La, la ♪ -♪ La, la, la, la, la, la, la ♪
-♪ ला, ला ♪ -♪ ला, ला, ला, ला, ला, ला ♪
-♪ La, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la ♪
-♪ ला, ला, ला , ला, ला, ला, ला, ला, ला ♪
-♪ La, la ♪ -♪ La, la, la, la, la, la, la ♪
-♪ ला, ला ♪ -♪ ला, ला, ला, ला, ला, ला ♪
-♪ La, la, la, la, la, la, la, la, la ♪
-♪ ला, ला, ला , ला, ला, ला, ला, ला, ला ♪
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
-(grunt in unison) -Hup!
(एक साथ गुर्राते हुए) -हप!
OZIANS: ♪ Save us from the Wicked ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ हमें दुष्टों से बचाओ ♪
♪ Every night, our voices wail ♪
♪ हर रात, हमारी आवाज़ें विलाप करती हैं ♪
-♪ Save us from this fear ♪ -(train whistle blows)
-♪ हमें इस भय से बचाओ ♪ -(ट्रेन की सीटी बजती है)
♪ And victimhood ♪
♪ और पीड़ित होना ♪
(train whistle blows)
(ट्रेन की सीटी बजती है)
-♪ We believe in Glinda ♪ -(confetti popping)
-♪ हमें ग्लिंडा पर भरोसा है ♪ -(कन्फ़ेटी फूटने की आवाज़)
♪ With her magic, she'll prevail ♪
♪ अपनी जादूई शक्तियों से वह विजयी होगी ♪
♪ She will make it end ♪
♪ वो इसे खत्म कर देगी ♪
♪ The way it should ♪
♪ जैसा होना चाहिए ♪
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
♪ When at last the Wicked is defeated ♪
♪ जब अंततः दुष्ट पराजित हो जाएगा ♪
♪ By the Good ♪
♪ अच्छे द्वारा ♪
♪ The Good ♪
♪ अच्छा ♪
♪ Wicked is defeated ♪
♪ दुष्ट पराजित हो गया ♪
-♪ By the Good. ♪ -(popping)
-♪ अच्छाई की कसम। ♪ -(पॉपिंग)
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
PFANNEE: There's a quoncert in Quox,
PFANNEE: क्वॉक्स में एक क्वॉन्सर्ट है,
if you want to attend, next week.
यदि आप आना चाहें, तो अगले सप्ताह आ सकते हैं।
GLINDA: Oh. Perhaps.
ग्लिंडा: ओह। शायद।
Uh, The Quadling Quorum wants to honor you.
अह, क्वाडलिंग कोरम आपको सम्मानित करना चाहता है।
They're just not sure for what yet.
उन्हें अभी यह पक्का नहीं पता कि वे किस लिए ऐसा करेंगे।
Good to hear.
सुनने में अच्छा।
And someone sent pastries.
और किसी ने पेस्ट्री भेजी।
(chuckles) Good for us.
(हंसते हुए) हमारे लिए अच्छा है।
Hey, send these to my hovel, please.
अरे, कृपया इन्हें मेरी झोपड़ी में भेज दो।
The gowns from last week?
पिछले हफ्ते वाले गाउन?
PFANNEE: Oh, maybe, uh, give to the under-fortunate.
फैनी: ओह, शायद, उह, जरूरतमंदों को दान दे दें।
-SHENSHEN: Oh, of course. -GLINDA: (gasps) Good idea.
-शेनशेन: ओह, बिल्कुल। -ग्लिंडा: (हैरान होकर) अच्छा विचार है।
-(grunting) -And, you know,
(घुरघुराते हुए) और, आप जानते हैं,
while we're at it, we really should
जब हम इस बारे में बात कर रहे हैं, तो हमें वास्तव में ऐसा करना चाहिए
look into trademarking the word "good."
"अच्छा" शब्द का ट्रेडमार्क कराने पर विचार करें ।
-Ooh. That's go-- -Ooh.
-ओह। ये तो बढ़िया है-- -ओह।
-I mean, I'm goosified. -(chuckles)
-मतलब, मैं तो हंस-हंस कर लाल हो गया हूँ। (हंसते हुए)
My follicles are screaming.
मेरे रोमछिद्र चीख रहे हैं।
-I love my job so much. -GLINDA: Aw. Good.
मुझे अपना काम बहुत पसंद है। -ग्लिंडा: ओह। अच्छा।
(gasps) Madame Morrible.
(हैरान होकर) मैडम मोर्रिबल।
Forgive me for keeping you waiting.
आपको इंतजार कराने के लिए मुझे क्षमा करें ।
I had no idea.
मुझे अनुमान नहीं था।
Has something happened? Is it Elphaba?
क्या कुछ हुआ है? क्या यह एल्फाबा है?
You mean the Wicked Witch?
आपका मतलब दुष्ट चुड़ैल से है?
Right, of course.
जी हाँ, बिल्कुल।
-Come in, come in. -SHENSHEN: Mrs. Morrible...
-अंदर आइए, अंदर आइए। -शेनशेन: श्रीमती मॉरिबल...
Would you like us to take minutes for you?
क्या आप चाहेंगे कि हम आपके लिए कार्यवाही का विवरण लिख लें?
...I c-- I can, I can get you, like, a little snack.
मैं... मैं आपके लिए थोड़ा सा नाश्ता ला सकता हूँ।
You want a little snack?
क्या आप थोड़ा नाश्ता करना चाहेंगे?
Like a cherry frazzle or a juice puff?
जैसे चेरी फ्रैज़ल या जूस पफ?
"Mrs. Morrible"?
"श्रीमती मॉरिबल"?
She's not married.
वह अविवाहित है।
You sh... (groans)
तुम... (कराहता है)
MADAME MORRIBLE: With the Yellow Brick Road
मैडम मॉरिबल: पीली ईंटों वाली सड़क के साथ
grand opening ahead and the Wicked Witch attacks
भव्य उद्घाटन की तैयारी जारी है और दुष्ट चुड़ैल हमला करती है।
growing bolder, the public is on edge.
जैसे-जैसे उनका साहस बढ़ता जा रहा है, जनता में डर का माहौल छा रहा है।
So it's more important than ever
इसलिए यह पहले से कहीं अधिक महत्वपूर्ण है।
that you lift everyone's spirits,
आप सभी का मनोबल बढ़ाते हैं।
as only you can.
जैसा कि केवल आप ही कर सकते हैं।
(chuckles) Accordingly.
(हंसते हुए) तदनुसार।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
Oh, Madame, I love it.
ओह, मैडम, मुझे यह बहुत पसंद आया।
What is it?
यह क्या है?
Your new mode of transport.
आपका नया परिवहन साधन।
Your very own vehicular spherical globule.
आपका अपना वाहननुमा गोलाकार पिंड।
So, like, a bubble?
तो, एक बुलबुला?
Sure.
ज़रूर।
(Madame Morrible sighs)
(मैडम मॉरिबल आह भरती हैं)
(Glinda gasps)
(ग्लिंडा हांफती है)
Was that supposed to happen?
क्या ऐसा होना चाहिए था?
It's all right.
ठीक ठाक है।
GLINDA: Are you sure?
ग्लिंडा: क्या आप निश्चित हैं?
Wha--
क्या--
Does that do what I think it does?
क्या यह वही काम करता है जो मैं सोच रहा हूँ?
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
(muffled): No!
(धीमी आवाज़ में): नहीं!
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
(muffled): I can't.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): मैं नहीं कर सकता।
(clearly): No way!
(स्पष्ट रूप से): बिलकुल नहीं!
(Glinda giggles, screams)
(ग्लिंडा खिलखिलाती है, चीखती है)
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
(muffled): I'm obsessulated.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): मैं जुनूनी हूँ।
The Wizard had it crafted especially for you.
जादूगर ने इसे खास आपके लिए बनवाया है।
His Ozness feels it vital that you, as our Good Witch,
उनके ओज़नेस को यह अत्यंत महत्वपूर्ण लगता है कि आप, हमारी अच्छी चुड़ैल के रूप में,
also be airborne.
हवा में भी उड़ सकते हैं।
(muffled): I agree.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): मैं सहमत हूँ।
But don't fret over your inability
लेकिन अपनी अक्षमता को लेकर परेशान न हों।
to produce any actual magic.
किसी भी तरह का वास्तविक जादू पैदा करने के लिए।
This invention will disguise your deficiency.
यह आविष्कार आपकी कमी को छुपा देगा।
The bubble's mechanism is cleverly concealed.
इस बुलबुले की कार्यप्रणाली को चतुराई से छिपाया गया है।
People will assume that you are causing it to float
लोग मान लेंगे कि आप ही इसे तैरा रहे हैं।
through your own witchly powers.
अपनी जादुई शक्तियों के माध्यम से।
-(chuckles) -So, just let them assume.
(हंसते हुए) -तो, उन्हें अनुमान लगाने दो।
Right.
सही।
But don't forget this.
लेकिन इसे मत भूलना।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
(exhales sharply)
(तेजी से सांस छोड़ते हुए)
The wand really sells it.
जादू की छड़ी ही इसकी असली खासियत है।
I'll see you at the opening ceremony.
मैं आपसे उद्घाटन समारोह में मिलूंगा ।
(muffled): Thank you so much.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): बहुत-बहुत धन्यवाद।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(children laughing)
(बच्चे हंस रहे हैं)
YOUNG GALINDA: A magic wand?
छोटी गैलिंडा: एक जादुई छड़ी?
CHILDREN: Happy birthday, Galinda.
बच्चे: जन्मदिन मुबारक हो, गैलिंडा।
(laughter)
(हँसी)
It's what I've wanted most of all.
यही तो मैं सबसे ज्यादा चाहता था।
Come on, give it a go.
चलो, एक बार कोशिश करके देखो।
-Yeah, try it out! -(excited chatter)
-हाँ, इसे आजमा कर देखो! -(उत्साहित होकर बातें)
(chanting): Magic! Magic! Magic! Magic! Magic!
(मंत्रोच्चारण करते हुए): जादू! जादू! जादू! जादू! जादू!
CHILD: Come on.
बच्चा: चलो।
(laughter)
(हँसी)
(children murmuring and whispering)
(बच्चे आपस में फुसफुसा रहे हैं)
Oh. (giggles)
ओह। (हंसती है)
I forgot to say the spell.
मैं मंत्र बोलना भूल गया।
-Oh, yeah. -(overlapping chatter)
-ओह, हाँ। -(आपस में बातचीत)
-The wand. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. -(giggling)
-जादू की छड़ी। हाँ। हाँ। हाँ। (हंसते हुए)
I hereby commandify that something magical shall happen!
मैं आदेश देता हूँ कि कुछ जादुई घटित हो!
-CHILD: She can't even make a spark. -(children murmuring)
-बच्चा: वह तो चिंगारी भी नहीं पैदा कर सकती । (बच्चे आपस में फुसफुसाते हैं)
Look! There's a rainbow.
देखो! वहाँ इंद्रधनुष है।
-CHILD: Wow.
(बच्चे आपस में फुसफुसा रहे हैं) -बच्चा: वाह!
Did you make that?
क्या तुमने इसे बनाया है?
Um...
एक...
Well, you know how I love rainbows.
वैसे, आपको तो पता ही है कि मुझे इंद्रधनुष कितना पसंद है।
-(Popsicle laughs) -(children cheering)
(पॉप्सिकल की हंसी) (बच्चे खुशी से चिल्ला रहे हैं)
(excited chatter)
(उत्साहित बातचीत)
CHILD: That's my friend!
बच्चा: वो मेरा दोस्त है!
(excited chatter continues)
(उत्साह से भरी बातचीत जारी है)
POPSICLE (singsongy): Go see the rainbow!
पॉप्सिकल (गाते हुए): जाओ इंद्रधनुष देखो!
MOMSIE: Isn't it fantastic?
मॉम्सी: है ना ये शानदार?
POPSICLE: Who is ready for some cake?
पॉप्सिकल: केक खाने के लिए कौन तैयार है?
-Go see Rosie and Posie. -(excited chatter)
-रोजी और पोसी से मिलने जाओ। (उत्साह से बातें)
MOMSIE: What's wrong, dearest?
मॉम्सी: क्या ग़लत है, प्रिये?
You got everything you wanted.
आपको वो सब कुछ मिल गया जो आप चाहते थे।
I know, but I want to be magical.
मुझे पता है, लेकिन मैं जादुई बनना चाहता हूँ।
For real.
वास्तव में।
And... I'm not.
और मैं नहीं हूँ।
Oh, but, darlingest, everyone loves you.
लेकिन, मेरी प्यारी, तुम्हें तो सब प्यार करते हैं।
Believe me, that's all you'll ever need.
यकीन मानिए, आपको बस इतना ही चाहिए होगा।
Where's that smile?
वो मुस्कान कहाँ गई?
That's my girl.
शाबाश मेरी बच्ची।
(lively chatter and laughter continues)
(हलचल और हंसी जारी है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Sweetheart, you coming?
प्रियतम, क्या तुम आ रही हो?
Come on!
चलो भी!
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
(cheering continues)
(जयकार जारी है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(Ozians exclaiming)
(ओज़ियन लोग विस्मय व्यक्त करते हैं)
(cheering continues)
(जयकार जारी है)
Glinda!
ग्लिंडा!
Fellow Ozians, good news.
ओज़ के साथियों, खुशखबरी!
Now, at last, all roads lead to the Wizard.
अब, अंततः, सभी रास्ते जादूगर की ओर ही जाते हैं।
♪ Oh, what a celebration we'll have today ♪
♪ ओह, आज हम कितना बड़ा उत्सव मनाएंगे ♪
♪ Thank Goodness ♪
♪ शुक्र है ♪
♪ Let's have a celebration the Glinda way ♪
♪ चलो ग्लिंडा के अंदाज़ में जश्न मनाते हैं ♪
♪ Finally, a day that's totally Wicked Witch-free ♪
♪ आखिरकार, एक ऐसा दिन जो पूरी तरह से दुष्ट चुड़ैल से मुक्त है ♪
♪ We couldn't be happier ♪
♪ हम बेहद खुश हैं ♪
♪ Thank Goodness ♪
♪ शुक्र है ♪
(cheering)
(जयकार)
MADAME MORRIBLE: Thank Goodness for you, Glinda,
मैडम मॉरिबल: शुक्र है तुम्हारा, ग्लिंडा!
and your handsome swain, Prince Fiyero,
और आपके सुंदर प्रेमी, राजकुमार फियेरो,
newly appointed captain of the Gale Force--
गेल फोर्स के नव नियुक्त कप्तान--
assembled by the Wizard himself to capture the Wicked Witch.
दुष्ट चुड़ैल को पकड़ने के लिए स्वयं जादूगर द्वारा एकत्रित किया गया ।
Tell us, Captain.
हमें बताइए, कप्तान जी।
How does it feel?
यह कैसी लगता है?
It's frustrating.
यह निराशाजनक है।
But I became captain to find her,
लेकिन मैं उसे ढूंढने के लिए कप्तान बना।
and I will keep on searching until I do.
और मैं तब तक खोजता रहूंगा जब तक मुझे वह मिल नहीं जाता।
-No! -(feedback squeals)
-नहीं! -(प्रतिक्रिया की चीखें)
Being engaged.
सगाई होना।
(Ozians gasping)
(ओज़ियन हांफ रहे हैं)
-(laughing) -(cheering)
(हंसते हुए) (खुशी मनाते हुए)
We're engaged?
संलग्न रहें?
Surprised?
हैरान?
Yes. (chuckles)
हां। (हंसते हुए)
Good. We hoped you'd be.
अच्छा। हमें उम्मीद थी कि आप ऐसा ही करेंगे।
Um, the Wizard and I.
उम, जादूगर और मैं।
(Ozians aahing)
(ओज़ियन आहें भरते हैं)
♪ We couldn't be happier ♪
♪ हम बेहद खुश हैं ♪
Right, dear?
ठीक है ना, प्रिय?
♪ Couldn't be happier ♪
♪ बेहद खुश हूँ ♪
♪ Right here ♪
♪ यहीं पर ♪
♪ Look what we've got, a fairy-tale plot ♪
♪ देखो हमें क्या मिला है, एक परीकथा जैसी कहानी ♪
♪ Our very own happy ending ♪
♪ हमारी अपनी सुखद कहानी का अंत ♪
-(Ozians aahing) -♪ Where we ♪
(ओज़ियन आहें भरते हुए) -♪ हम कहाँ हैं ♪
♪ Couldn't be happier ♪
♪ बेहद खुश हूँ ♪
True, dear?
सच है, प्रिय?
♪ And we're happy to share ♪
♪ और हमें इसे साझा करने में खुशी है ♪
♪ Our ending vicariously ♪
♪ हमारा परोक्ष अंत ♪
♪ With all of you ♪
♪ आप सभी के साथ ♪
♪ He couldn't look handsomer ♪
♪ वह बेहद आकर्षक लग रहे थे ♪
♪ I couldn't feel humbler ♪
♪ मैं इससे अधिक विनम्र महसूस नहीं कर सकता ♪
♪ We couldn't be happier ♪
♪ हम बेहद खुश हैं ♪
♪ Because happy is what happens ♪
♪ क्योंकि खुशी ही तो मिलती है ♪
♪ When all your dreams come true ♪
♪ जब आपके सारे सपने सच हो जाएं ♪
(Ozians gasping, cheering)
(ओज़ियन हांफते और जयकारे लगाते हैं)
MADAME MORRIBLE: And, Glinda, dear, we are happy for you.
मैडम मॉरिबल: और, प्रिय ग्लिंडा, हमें आपके लिए खुशी है।
As Press Secretary, I've striven to ensure
प्रेस सचिव के रूप में, मैंने यह सुनिश्चित करने का प्रयास किया है
that all of Oz knows the story of your braverism
ऑस्ट्रेलिया के सभी लोग आपकी बहादुरी की कहानी जानते हैं।
in the face of the terrifying
भयानक परिस्थितियों का सामना करते हुए
Wicked Witch of the West.
पश्चिम की दुष्ट चुड़ैल।
(Ozians gasping)
(ओज़ियन हांफ रहे हैं)
♪ I hear she has an extra eye ♪
♪ मैंने सुना है कि उसकी एक अतिरिक्त आंख है ♪
-♪ That always remains awake ♪ -(Ozians murmuring)
-♪ जो हमेशा जागृत रहता है ♪ -(ओज़ियन आपस में बुदबुदा रहे हैं)
♪ I hear that she can shed her skin ♪
♪ मैंने सुना है कि वह अपनी त्वचा उतार सकती है ♪
-♪ As easily as a snake ♪ -(Ozians gasping)
-♪ एक साँप की तरह आसानी से ♪ -(ओज़ियन हांफते हुए)
♪ I hear some rebel animals ♪
♪ मुझे कुछ विद्रोही जानवरों की आवाजें सुनाई दे रही हैं ♪
♪ Are giving her food and shelter ♪
♪ उसे खाना और आश्रय दे रहे हैं ♪
♪ I hear her soul is so unclean ♪
♪ मैंने सुना है उसकी आत्मा बहुत अपवित्र है ♪
♪ Pure water can melt her ♪
♪ शुद्ध जल उसे पिघला सकता है ♪
-Mmm. Darling? -OZIANS: ♪ Melt her ♪
-हम्म। डार्लिंग? -ओज़ियंस: ♪ उसे पिघला दो ♪
♪ Please, somebody, go and melt her ♪
♪ कोई जाकर उसे पिघला दे ♪
People are so empty-headed,
लोग कितने खाली दिमाग वाले हैं,
-they'll believe anything. -(chuckles softly)
वे किसी भी बात पर विश्वास कर लेंगे। (हल्की हंसी)
If you'll excuse us just a clock-tick. (chuckles)
अगर आप हमें बस एक पल का समय देंगे तो अच्छा होगा। (हंसते हुए)
Come with me, dearest.
मेरे साथ आओ, प्रियतम।
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
What is going on?
क्या हो रहा है?
People are watching.
लोग देख रहे हैं।
I can't just stand there grinning,
मैं वहाँ यूँ ही खड़े होकर मुस्कुरा नहीं सकता ।
pretending to go along with all this.
इन सब बातों से सहमत होने का नाटक करना ।
Do you think I like hearing them say
क्या आपको लगता है कि मुझे उनकी बातें सुनना पसंद है?
those awful things about her? I hate it.
उसकी वो भयानक बातें? मुझे उनसे नफरत है।
Then what are we doing here? Let's go. Let's go.
तो फिर हम यहाँ क्या कर रहे हैं? चलो चलें। चलो चलें।
-Let's just get out of here. -I-I can't.
-चलो यहाँ से चलते हैं। -मैं नहीं चल सकता।
I can't when there are people looking to me
जब लोग मेरी ओर देख रहे हों तो मैं ऐसा नहीं कर सकता।
to raise their spirits.
उनका मनोबल बढ़ाने के लिए।
You can't leave because you can't resist this.
आप जा नहीं सकते क्योंकि आप इसका विरोध नहीं कर सकते।
That's the truth.
यही सच है।
Well, maybe I can't.
खैर, शायद मैं नहीं कर सकता।
Is that so wrong?
क्या यह इतना गलत है?
I mean, who could?
मतलब, कौन कर सकता है?
Well, you know who could.
खैर, आप जानते हैं कि कौन कर सकता है।
We both know who could and who has.
हम दोनों जानते हैं कि कौन ऐसा कर सकता था और किसने ऐसा किया है।
And I have to find her,
और मुझे उसे ढूंढना होगा।
because if someone else gets there first, she...
क्योंकि अगर कोई और पहले वहां पहुंच गया तो...
Fiyero, I'm worried for her, too.
फियेरो, मुझे भी उसकी चिंता है।
And I miss her.
और मुझे उसकी याद आती है।
Can't you see she doesn't want to be found?
क्या आपको नहीं दिख रहा कि वह नहीं चाहती कि उसे ढूंढा जाए?
You've got to face it.
आपको इसे स्वीकार करना ही होगा।
She's made her choice.
उसने अपना फैसला कर लिया है।
You're right.
आप ठीक कह रहे हैं।
And, look...
और देखो...
...if it makes you happy, of course I'll marry you.
...अगर इससे आपको खुशी मिलती है, तो मैं आपसे शादी जरूर करूँगी।
It'll make you happy, too, right?
इससे आपको भी खुशी मिलेगी, है ना?
You know me. I'm always happy.
आप मुझे जानते ही हैं। मैं हमेशा खुश रहता हूँ।
Fiyero.
फियेरो।
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
Thanks plenty, dearest.
बहुत-बहुत धन्यवाद, प्रियतम।
He's, um... he's gone to fetch me a refreshment.
वो... वो मेरे लिए कुछ जलपान लाने गया है।
(Ozians aahing)
(ओज़ियन आहें भरते हैं)
He's so thoughtful that way.
वह इस मामले में बहुत विचारशील है।
♪ That's why ♪
♪ इसीलिए ♪
♪ I couldn't be happier ♪
♪ मैं इससे ज़्यादा खुश नहीं हो सकता ♪
♪ No, I couldn't be happier ♪
♪ नहीं, मैं इससे ज़्यादा खुश नहीं हो सकता ♪
♪ Though it is, I admit ♪
♪ हालांकि, मैं यह स्वीकार करता हूँ ♪
♪ The tiniest bit ♪
♪ बिलकुल थोड़ा सा ♪
♪ Unlike I anticipated ♪
♪ जैसा मैंने अनुमान लगाया था, वैसा नहीं ♪
♪ But I couldn't be happier ♪
♪ लेकिन मैं इससे ज़्यादा खुश नहीं हो सकता ♪
♪ Simply couldn't be happier ♪
♪ बेहद खुश हूँ ♪
Well, not "simply."
खैर, "सरलता से" नहीं।
♪ 'Cause getting your dreams ♪
♪ क्योंकि अपने सपनों को पाना ♪
♪ It's strange, but it seems ♪
♪ यह अजीब है, लेकिन ऐसा लगता है ♪
♪ A little, well, complicated ♪
♪ थोड़ा, मतलब, जटिल ♪
♪ There's a kind of a sort of ♪
♪ एक तरह का ♪
♪ Cost ♪
♪ लागत ♪
♪ There's a couple of things get ♪
♪ कुछ बातें हैं जो समझ में आती हैं ♪
♪ Lost ♪
♪ खो गया ♪
♪ There are bridges you cross you didn't know you crossed ♪
♪ कुछ ऐसे पुल होते हैं जिन्हें आप पार कर लेते हैं, लेकिन आपको पता भी नहीं होता कि आपने उन्हें पार कर लिया है ♪
♪ Until you've crossed ♪
♪ जब तक तुम पार नहीं कर लेते ♪
♪ And if that joy ♪
♪ और अगर वह खुशी ♪
♪ That thrill ♪
♪ वो रोमांच ♪
♪ Doesn't thrill like you think it will ♪
♪ यह उतना रोमांचक नहीं है जितना आप सोचते हैं ♪
♪ Still ♪
♪ अभी भी ♪
♪ With this perfect finale ♪
♪ इस शानदार समापन के साथ ♪
♪ The cheers and the ballyhoo ♪
♪ जयकारे और शोरगुल ♪
♪ Who wouldn't be happier? ♪
♪ भला कौन इतना खुश नहीं होगा? ♪
♪ So I couldn't be happier ♪
♪ मैं इससे ज़्यादा खुश नहीं हो सकता ♪
♪ Because happy is what happens ♪
♪ क्योंकि खुशी ही तो मिलती है ♪
♪ When all your dreams ♪
♪ जब आपके सारे सपने ♪
♪ Come true ♪
♪ सच हो जाए ♪
Well, isn't it?
है ना?
♪ Happy is what happens ♪
♪ खुशी ही सब कुछ है ♪
♪ When your dreams ♪
♪ जब आपके सपने ♪
♪ Come true ♪
♪ सच हो जाए ♪
OZIANS: ♪ We love you, Glinda, if we may be so frank ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ हम आपसे प्यार करते हैं, ग्लिंडा, अगर हम खुलकर कह सकें तो ♪
♪ Thank Goodness ♪
♪ शुक्र है ♪
♪ For all this joy, we know who we've got to thank ♪
♪ इस सारी खुशी के लिए, हम जानते हैं कि हमें किसका धन्यवाद करना चाहिए ♪
♪ Thank Goodness ♪
♪ शुक्र है ♪
♪ That means the Wizard, Glinda ♪
♪ इसका मतलब है जादूगरनी, ग्लिंडा ♪
♪ And fiancé ♪
♪ और मंगेतर ♪
♪ They couldn't be Goodlier ♪
♪ वे इससे ज़्यादा अच्छे नहीं हो सकते ♪
♪ She couldn't be lovelier ♪
♪ वह बेहद प्यारी है ♪
♪ We couldn't be luckier ♪
♪ हम इससे ज़्यादा भाग्यशाली नहीं हो सकते ♪
♪ I couldn't be happier ♪
♪ मैं इससे ज़्यादा खुश नहीं हो सकता ♪
-♪ Thank Goodness ♪
-♪ शुक्र है ♪
♪ Today ♪
♪ आज ♪
♪ Thank Goodness for today ♪
♪ आज के लिए ईश्वर का धन्यवाद ♪
-(fireworks popping, whistling) -♪ Thank Goodness ♪
(पटाखों की आवाज़, सीटी की आवाज़) - ♪ शुक्र है ♪
♪ For today. ♪
♪ आज के लिए। ♪
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
-(whooshing) -(Ozians gasping, murmuring)
(तेज़ हवा की आवाज़) (ओज़ियन हांफते और बुदबुदाते हैं)
It's the Wicked Witch!
ये तो दुष्ट चुड़ैल है!
Take cover!
कवर ले!
-Mount up! -(Ozians clamoring, screaming)
-तैयार हो जाओ! -(ओज़ियन चिल्ला रहे हैं, चीख रहे हैं)
(fireworks popping)
(पटाखों की आवाज)
MADAME MORRIBLE: Glinda!
मैडम मॉरिबल: ग्लिंडा!
Take cover, everyone!
सभी लोग सुरक्षित स्थान पर चले जाएं!
GLINDA: Everyone, please, don't be alarmed.
ग्लिंडा: कृपया सभी लोग घबराएं नहीं।
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
She won't hurt you. It's okay.
वह तुम्हें नुकसान नहीं पहुंचाएगी। चिंता मत करो।
She wants to kill us all!
वह हम सबको मारना चाहती है!
Look!
देखना!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(clamoring and screaming continue)
(शोर-शराबा और चीख-पुकार जारी है)
Gale Force, go!
तेज हवा, आगे बढ़ो!
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
-(horse neighing) -FIYERO: Hyah!
(घोड़े की हिनहिनाहट) -फियेरो: हयाह!
Fiyero!
फियेरो!
Hyah! Come on! Hyah!
हयाह! चलो! हयाह!
No, come.
नहीं, कैसे?
-(monkeys hooting) -(soldiers shouting)
(बंदरों की आवाज) (सैनिकों के चिल्लाने की आवाज)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
(grunting, panting)
(घुरघुराहट, हांफना)
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
Halt!
रुको!
(horses sputtering softly)
(घोड़े धीरे-धीरे हांफ रहे हैं)
(birds calling in distance)
(दूर से पक्षियों की चहचहाहट सुनाई दे रही है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(breathing heavily)
(तेजी से सांस लेते हुए)
SOLDIER: Captain, do you see anything?
सिपाही: कप्तान, क्या आपको कुछ दिखाई दे रहा है?
No.
नहीं।
Come on.
चलो भी।
We must not rest until we capture that Wicked Witch.
जब तक हम उस दुष्ट चुड़ैल को पकड़ नहीं लेते, तब तक हमें चैन से नहीं बैठना चाहिए ।
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
Come on! Let's go!
चलो चलते हैं!
-Move out. -Fall in.
-बाहर निकलो। -अंदर आ जाओ।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(whooshing)
(तेज़ हवा की आवाज़)
(frustrated grunt)
(निराशा भरी आह)
Fiyero.
फियेरो।
Even you.
यहां तक ​​कि आप।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(faint laughter)
(हल्की हंसी)
(birds chirping)
(पक्षियों का चहचहाना)
(wind whistling softly)
(हवा की हल्की सीटी की आवाज)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(door opens)
(दरवाजा खुलता है)
AVARIC: Madam Governor?
एवरिक: मैडम गवर्नर?
That proposed new regulation, the Animal Anti-Motility law.
वह प्रस्तावित नया नियम, पशु गतिहीनता विरोधी कानून।
What law?
कौन सा कानून?
Animals would need a permit to travel.
जानवरों को यात्रा करने के लिए परमिट की आवश्यकता होगी ।
AVARIC: Munchkinland is the one place
एवरिक: मंचकिनलैंड ही वह जगह है
in Oz it hasn't been ratified.
ऑस्ट्रेलिया में इसे अभी तक मंजूरी नहीं मिली है।
The League of Governors is urging you to sign.
गवर्नर्स लीग आपसे हस्ताक्षर करने का आग्रह कर रही है।
Nessa, you're not going to sign that.
नेसा, तुम इस पर हस्ताक्षर नहीं करने वाली हो।
But if I don't...
लेकिन अगर मैं ऐसा नहीं करता...
people will say, "She's just like her sister."
लोग कहेंगे, "वह बिल्कुल अपनी बहन जैसी है।"
Give us a clock-tick, Avaric.
हमें घड़ी की टिक-टिक बताओ, अवारिक।
Boq, forgive me.
बोक, मुझे माफ कर दो।
It's just that Elphaba abandoned me when I needed her.
बात बस इतनी सी है कि जब मुझे एल्फाबा की सबसे ज्यादा जरूरत थी, तब उसने मुझे छोड़ दिया।
She didn't even come see me when Father died.
पिताजी की मृत्यु के समय वह मुझसे मिलने तक नहीं आई ।
Only you did that.
यह सिर्फ तुमने किया।
Oz only knows how I'd have coped
ओज़ ही जानता है कि मैं कैसे सामना करता।
with all of this without you.
तुम्हारे बिना, इन सब के साथ।
And I'm glad I could be there for you.
और मुझे खुशी है कि मैं आपके लिए वहां मौजूद रह सका।
But I've been thinking for a while now...
लेकिन मैं काफी समय से इस बारे में सोच रहा हूँ...
Yes?
हाँ?
I think it's time I moved on.
मुझे लगता है कि अब आगे बढ़ने का समय आ गया है।
I see.
अच्छा ऐसा है।
Well, if that's how you feel,
ठीक है, अगर आपको ऐसा लगता है,
I think it's best you leave.
मुझे लगता है कि आपके लिए चले जाना ही बेहतर होगा।
Now.
अब।
Nessa, this won't be the last time we'll see each other.
नेसा, यह हमारी आखिरी मुलाकात नहीं होगी ।
Oh, I know.
ओह, मुझे पता है।
(door opens, closes)
(दरवाजा खुलता है, बंद होता है)
-ANNOUNCER: Attention, passengers. -(whistle blowing)
-घोषक: यात्रियों ध्यान दें। (सीटी बजाई गई)
This is the final boarding for the Emerald City Unlimited.
एमराल्ड सिटी अनलिमिटेड के लिए यह आखिरी बोर्डिंग है ।
Doors will be closing shortly.
दरवाजे जल्द ही बंद हो जाएंगे।
Please step inside and make way for boarding passengers.
कृपया अंदर आएं और यात्रियों को चढ़ने के लिए जगह दें।
(busy chatter)
(व्यस्त बातचीत)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
ANNOUNCER: Visiting someone special?
उद्घोषक: क्या आप किसी खास व्यक्ति से मिलने जा रहे हैं?
Get a new Ozfit.
एक नया ओज़फिट खरीदें।
Visit the Wizard's Emporium in downtown Emerald City.
एमराल्ड सिटी के डाउनटाउन में स्थित विजार्ड्स एम्पोरियम में जाएँ ।
-(knocks) -TICKET ASSISTANT: Next.
(खटखटाहट) - टिकट सहायक: अगला।
Oh.
ओह।
Excuse me. Um, my train is boarding in...
माफ़ कीजिए। मेरी ट्रेन... में चढ़ने वाली है।
Travel permit?
यात्रा परमिट?
-What? -All Munchkins are forbidden
-क्या? -सभी मंचकिन्स प्रतिबंधित हैं
to leave Munchkinland
मंचकिनलैंड छोड़ने के लिए
without express written permission of the Governor.
राज्यपाल की स्पष्ट लिखित अनुमति के बिना ।
She insisted it go into effect immediately.
उन्होंने जोर देकर कहा कि इसे तुरंत लागू किया जाए।
ANNOUNCER: ...reminder to all passengers...
उद्घोषक: ... सभी यात्रियों को याद दिलाना...
MUNCHKIN PARENT 1: Stop pushing me.
नन्हे अभिभावक 1: मुझे धक्का देना बंद करो।
-MUNCHKIN PARENT 2: Elsa. -TRAIN STATION OFFICIAL: Go!
-मंचकिन अभिभावक 2: एल्सा। -ट्रेन स्टेशन अधिकारी: जाओ!
-What's happening? -Keep your hands off my family.
-क्या हो रहा है? -मेरे परिवार से दूर रहो।
I don't want to hear it, Munchkins.
मैं यह सुनना नहीं चाहता, मुंचकिन्स।
Move! Forward now, Munchkins.
चलो! आगे बढ़ो, नन्हे बच्चों!
GUARD: Go.
गार्ड: जाओ।
MUNCHKIN PARENT 1: This is outrageous.
नन्हे अभिभावक 1: यह तो घोर अन्याय है।
-You cannot treat us like this. -Go!
आप हमारे साथ ऐसा व्यवहार नहीं कर सकते। -जाओ!
Move along, Munchkins.
आगे बढ़ो, नन्हे बच्चों।
TICKET ASSISTANT: Next.
टिकट सहायक: अगला।
MUNCHKIN PARENT 2: This is not the Oz I know.
मंचकिन अभिभावक 2: यह वह ओज़ नहीं है जिसे मैं जानता हूँ।
-This is un-Ozian. -Back in line.
-यह ओज़ियन शैली के विपरीत है। -वापस लाइन में लगो।
-Step back. What did I say? -(Munchkins clamoring)
-पीछे हटो। मैंने क्या कहा? -(छोटे बच्चे शोर मचाने लगे)
Step-- Munchkins, step back.
कदम-- नन्हे-मुन्चे, पीछे हट जाओ।
Back in line.
वापस लाइन में।
(fabric rustling)
(कपड़े की सरसराहट)
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(animals bellowing and calling)
(जानवरों की दहाड़ और पुकार)
GUIDE ANIMAL: Watch your footing.
मार्गदर्शक पशु: संभलकर चलें।
Next group. Come on, children.
अगला समूह। चलो बच्चों।
Let's move. We have to leave now.
चलो चलते हैं। हमें अभी निकलना होगा।
GUIDE ANIMAL 2: Stay together!
मार्गदर्शक पशु 2: साथ रहो!
-Come along now. -(animals grunting, calling)
चलो अब। (जानवरों की गुर्राहट और पुकार)
Keep moving.
चलते रहो।
Eyes on your children, please.
कृपया अपने बच्चों पर नजर रखें।
Don't worry, I'm with you. I'll never leave you.
चिंता मत करो, मैं तुम्हारे साथ हूँ। मैं तुम्हें कभी नहीं छोडूंगा।
Don't go too fast.
ज्यादा तेज मत जाओ।
-What is all this? -GUIDE ANIMAL: Watch your step.
-यह सब क्या है? -मार्गदर्शक पशु: संभलकर चलें।
ELPHABA: What are you doing?
एल्फाबा: तुम क्या कर रहे हो?
Come, children. Quickly.
आओ बच्चों। जल्दी करो।
We must get out of Oz.
हमें ऑस्ट्रेलिया से बाहर निकलना होगा।
Don't do this. Please.
ऐसा मत करो। कृपया।
-Keep moving. -Don't leave Oz.
चलते रहो। ऑस्ट्रेलिया मत छोड़ो।
Join with me. Help me fight the Wizard.
मेरे साथ जुड़ो। जादूगर से लड़ने में मेरी मदद करो।
(scoffs) And wait for the monkeys to carry us off?
(हंसते हुए) और बंदरों के हमें उठाकर ले जाने का इंतज़ार करें?
That's what happens to animals who speak out.
बोलने वाले जानवरों के साथ यही होता है ।
And they're never seen again.
और फिर वे कभी दिखाई नहीं देते।
No.
नहीं।
Oz wouldn't be Oz without all of you.
आप सबके बिना ओज़, ओज़ नहीं होता ।
And I know you're frightened, but this is home.
और मुझे पता है कि तुम डरे हुए हो, लेकिन यही तुम्हारा घर है।
Belongs to all of us.
यह हम सभी का है।
-DULCIBEAR: Elphaba. -(animals gasping, murmuring)
-डुल्सिबियर: एल्फाबा। (जानवर हांफ रहे हैं, बड़बड़ा रहे हैं)
(birds squawking)
(पक्षियों की चहचहाहट)
Dulcibear.
जानेमन।
Oh, little one.
ओह, नन्हे बच्चे।
I've missed your bear hugs.
मुझे तुम्हारे प्यार भरे गले लगने की बहुत याद आई।
(Dulcibear sighs)
(डुल्सिबियर आह भरती है)
We can't stay here.
हम यहां नहीं रुक सकते।
It's become rotten.
यह सड़ चुका है।
There's only one thing left for us to do:
अब हमारे लिए केवल एक ही काम बचा है :
escape through that tunnel to The Place Beyond Oz.
उस सुरंग से होते हुए ओज़ से परे की जगह पर भाग निकलें।
They say The Place Beyond Oz is just...
वे कहते हैं कि ओज़ से परे की जगह बस...
...emptiness.
...शून्यता।
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
How will you survive?
आप कैसे जीवित रहेंगे?
How will you survive here?
आप यहां कैसे जीवित रहेंगे?
No one in Oz will be happy until you're dead.
जब तक तुम मर नहीं जाते, ऑस्ट्रेलिया में कोई खुश नहीं होगा ।
(animals murmuring)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Why would you want to stay?
आप यहाँ क्यों रुकना चाहेंगे?
I don't know.
मुझें नहीं पता।
♪ Why do I love this place ♪
♪ मुझे यह जगह इतनी पसंद क्यों है ♪
♪ That's never loved me? ♪
♪ जिसने मुझसे कभी प्यार नहीं किया? ♪
♪ A place that seems to be devolving ♪
♪ एक ऐसी जगह जो पतन की ओर अग्रसर प्रतीत होती है ♪
♪ And even wanting to ♪
♪ और यहाँ तक कि चाहत भी ♪
♪ But Oz is more than just a place ♪
♪ लेकिन ओज़ सिर्फ एक जगह से कहीं अधिक है ♪
♪ It's a promise, an idea ♪
♪ यह एक वादा है, एक विचार है ♪
♪ And I want to help make it come true ♪
♪ और मैं इसे सच करने में मदद करना चाहता हूँ ♪
♪ Why should a land have so much meaning ♪
♪ किसी भूमि का इतना महत्व क्यों होना चाहिए ♪
♪ When dark times befall it? ♪
♪ जब इस पर अंधकारमय समय आ पड़े? ♪
♪ It's only land ♪
♪ ये तो बस ज़मीन है ♪
♪ Made of dirt and rock and loam ♪
♪ मिट्टी, पत्थर और दोमट मिट्टी से बना ♪
♪ It's just a place that's familiar ♪
♪ यह बस एक जानी-पहचानी जगह है ♪
♪ And home's just what we call it ♪
♪ और घर तो बस वही है जिसे हम कहते हैं ♪
♪ But there's no place like home ♪
♪ लेकिन घर जैसा कोई स्थान नहीं है ♪
♪ Don't we all know ♪
♪ क्या हम सब नहीं जानते ♪
♪ There's no place like home ♪
♪ घर जैसा कोई स्थान नहीं ♪
Try to understand.
समझने की कोशिश करें।
We just can't fight anymore.
हम अब और लड़ नहीं सकते।
We have to.
हमें करना ही होगा।
(animals murmuring)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
♪ When you feel you can't fight anymore ♪
♪ जब आपको लगे कि आप अब और लड़ नहीं सकते ♪
♪ Just tell yourself ♪
♪ बस खुद से कहो ♪
♪ There's no place like home ♪
♪ घर जैसा कोई स्थान नहीं ♪
♪ When you feel it's not worth fighting for ♪
♪ जब आपको लगे कि इसके लिए लड़ना व्यर्थ है ♪
♪ Compel yourself ♪
♪ स्वयं को विवश करो ♪
♪ Because there's no place like home ♪
♪ क्योंकि घर जैसा कोई और स्थान नहीं है ♪
♪ When you want to leave ♪
♪ जब आप जाना चाहें ♪
♪ Discouraged and resigned ♪
♪ निराश और हताश ♪
♪ That's what they want you to do ♪
♪ वे यही चाहते हैं कि तुम ऐसा करो ♪
♪ But think how you will grieve for all you leave behind ♪
♪ लेकिन सोचो कि तुम अपने पीछे छोड़ी गई हर चीज़ के लिए कितना शोक मनाओगे ♪
♪ Oz belongs to you, too ♪
♪ ओज़ तुम्हारा भी है ♪
(animals murmuring)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
♪ Those who would take it from you ♪
♪ जो इसे आपसे छीनना चाहते हैं ♪
♪ Spout a lie to sell yourself ♪
♪ झूठ बोलकर खुद को बेचो ♪
♪ You go their way or go ♪
♪ तुम उनके रास्ते जाओ या फिर चले जाओ ♪
♪ It's them we'll be defeating ♪
♪ हम उन्हीं को परास्त करेंगे ♪
♪ If we keep on repeating ♪
♪ अगर हम इसे बार-बार दोहराते रहेंगे ♪
♪ There's no place like home ♪
♪ घर जैसा कोई स्थान नहीं ♪
♪ There's no place ♪
♪ कोई जगह नहीं है ♪
♪ Like home ♪
♪ घर जैसा ♪
♪ There's no place like home ♪
♪ घर जैसा कोई स्थान नहीं ♪
(hooting)
(हूटिंग)
♪ If we just keep fighting for it ♪
♪ अगर हम इसके लिए लड़ते रहें ♪
♪ We will win back and restore it ♪
♪ हम इसे वापस जीतेंगे और पुनर्स्थापित करेंगे ♪
♪ There's no place ♪
♪ कोई जगह नहीं है ♪
♪ Like... ♪
♪ पसंद है... ♪
-Don't listen to her! (gasps) -(animals gasping)
-उसकी बात मत सुनो! (सांस फूलना) -(जानवर हांफने लगते हैं)
(animals murmuring)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
(whimpers)
(सिसकते हुए)
At night, when I close my eyes,
रात में, जब मैं अपनी आँखें बंद करता हूँ,
I still see that green face.
मुझे अभी भी वह हरा चेहरा दिखाई देता है।
(whimpers)
(सिसकते हुए)
I can't believe it. Is that you?
मुझे यकीन नहीं हो रहा। क्या ये तुम हो?
Stay back!
रुको!
When I was just a cub,
जब मैं छोटा बच्चा था,
she snatched me from the only home I ever knew.
उसने मुझे मेरे इकलौते घर से छीन लिया, जिसे मैं हमेशा से जानता था।
ELPHABA: You were in a cage.
एल्फाबा: तुम एक पिंजरे में थे।
If I'd have left you there,
अगर मैं तुम्हें वहीं छोड़ देता,
you would never have learned to speak.
तुम कभी बोलना नहीं सीख पाते।
They say she's the one who gave the monkeys wings
कहते हैं कि उसी ने बंदरों को पंख दिए।
and gave the Wizard his spies.
और उसने जादूगर को अपने जासूस सौंप दिए।
-ANIMAL: Is this true? -(animals murmuring)
-जानवर: क्या यह सच है? (जानवरों की भनभनाहट)
-It's true. -(animals gasping)
-यह सच है। (जानवर हांफने लगते हैं)
I cast that spell.
मैंने वह जादू किया।
And I have to live with that.
और मुझे इसके साथ जीना होगा।
(screeches)
(चीखें)
If I'd have known I was being tricked,
अगर मुझे पता होता कि मुझे धोखा दिया जा रहा है,
if I'd have known why, I would never have...
अगर मुझे वजह पता होती, तो मैं ऐसा कभी नहीं करता...
-The Wizard lies. -(animals chittering)
-जादूगर झूठ बोलता है। (जानवरों की चहचहाहट)
I can prove it. And if we stand together...
मैं इसे साबित कर सकता हूँ। और अगर हम सब साथ खड़े हों...
Dulcibear!
जानेमन!
Little one,
एक छोटा सा,
I know you'll keep fighting, because I know you.
मुझे पता है कि तुम लड़ते रहोगे, क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता हूं।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Thank you, Boq.
धन्यवाद, बोक।
Perhaps a friendly game of cards once I'm done working?
शायद काम खत्म होने के बाद हम दोस्तों के साथ ताश का एक दोस्ताना खेल खेल लें ?
Whatever you say, Madam Governor.
आप जो चाहें कहें, महोदया राज्यपाल।
I asked you to call me Nessa.
मैंने आपसे मुझे नेसा कहकर बुलाने के लिए कहा था।
Remember?
याद करना?
Boq.
बगीचा।
Never mind. I'll call you when I've finished.
कोई बात नहीं। काम खत्म होने पर मैं आपको फोन कर दूंगा ।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(wind whistling softly)
(हवा की हल्की सीटी की आवाज)
Now, who could have left that door open?
अब भला कौन उस दरवाजे को खुला छोड़ सकता था ?
-(Nessarose gasps) -I did.
(नेसारोज़ हांफते हुए बोली) -मैंने किया।
It's so good to see you.
आपको देखना बहुत अच्छा लग रहा है।
Why are you here?
तुम यहां क्यों हो?
I've tried to keep you out of all of this, but...
मैंने आपको इन सब बातों से दूर रखने की पूरी कोशिश की, लेकिन...
I need you.
मुझे तुम्हारी जरूरत है।
Thought you might have come to apologize.
मुझे लगा था कि आप माफी मांगने आए होंगे ।
Apologize?
क्षमा माँगना?
Our father died of shame,
हमारे पिता शर्म से मर गए।
and you didn't even bother to show up.
और तुम तो आने की जहमत तक नहीं उठाई।
You might at least pretend to be sorry.
कम से कम माफी मांगने का नाटक तो कर सकते हो।
For what? He hated me.
किसलिए? वह मुझसे नफरत करता था।
That's a Wicked thing to say.
यह कहना बहुत ही गलत बात है।
No, it's not.
नहीं यह नहीं।
It's just the truth.
यही तो सच्चाई है।
Do you know why?
आप जानते हैं क्यों?
What does it matter now?
अब इससे क्या फर्क पड़ता है?
You're right.
आप ठीक कह रहे हैं।
Doesn't matter.
कोई फर्क नहीं पड़ता।
Because it's just us.
क्योंकि यहाँ सिर्फ हम ही हैं।
You're the Governor. People will listen to you,
आप राज्यपाल हैं। लोग आपकी बात सुनेंगे।
-and together, we... -Why should I help you?
और साथ मिलकर हम... मुझे आपकी मदद क्यों करनी चाहिए?
You fly around Oz with that book,
आप उस किताब के साथ ऑस्ट्रेलिया की सैर करते हैं ।
helping animals you've never even met,
उन जानवरों की मदद करना जिनसे आप कभी मिले भी नहीं हैं,
and not once have you ever thought
और तुमने कभी एक बार भी नहीं सोचा
-to use your powers to help me. -You never wanted my help.
-अपनी शक्तियों का इस्तेमाल मेरी मदद करने के लिए करो। -तुमने कभी मेरी मदद नहीं चाही।
I do now!
मैं अब करुँ!
I want to go back to the way we were at school.
मैं स्कूल के दिनों की तरह सब कुछ फिर से जीना चाहता हूँ ।
That night when Boq told me I was beautiful.
उस रात जब बोक ने मुझसे कहा कि मैं खूबसूरत हूं।
(faint ballroom chatter)
(हल्की-सी बॉलरूम की बातचीत)
It was the first time I ever wore these shoes.
मैंने ये जूते पहली बार पहने थे।
There was music.
वहाँ संगीत बज रहा था।
(inhales deeply)
(गहरी सांस लेता है)
And everything was still possible.
और सब कुछ अभी भी संभव था ।
♪ That night at the Ozdust ♪
♪ उस रात ओज़डस्ट में ♪
♪ Boq danced with me there ♪
♪ बोक ने मेरे साथ वहाँ नृत्य किया ♪
♪ And it felt like he loved me then ♪
♪ और तब मुझे ऐसा लगा जैसे वो मुझसे प्यार करता हो ♪
♪ That night when I felt I was floating on air ♪
♪ वो रात जब मुझे ऐसा लगा जैसे मैं हवा में तैर रहा हूँ ♪
♪ I want to feel that again ♪
♪ मैं उस एहसास को फिर से महसूस करना चाहता हूँ ♪
Make me feel that again!
मुझे फिर से वही एहसास दिलाओ!
Nessa, I wish there was something I could do, but...
नेसा, काश मैं कुछ कर पाती, लेकिन...
(wind whistling softly)
(हवा की हल्की सीटी की आवाज)
"Ambulahn dare, pahto, pahpoot.
"अम्बुलाहन हिम्मत, पहतो, पहपूत।"
"Ambulahn dasca,
"एम्बुलेंस,
-lahfenahto." -What are you doing?
-lahfenahto." -तुम क्या कर रहे हो?
-"Ambulahn dare, pahto, pahpoot. -(faint rumbling)
-"एम्बुलेंस डेयर, पाटो, पाहपूट. -(धीमी गड़गड़ाहट)
-Ambulahn dasca, caldapess." -Oh.
-एम्बुलेंस डस्का, कैल्डैपेस।"</i > -ओह।
-Oh, my shoes. -"Lahfenahto, lahfenahtum."
-ओह, मेरे जूते। -"लाहफेनाटो, लाहफेनातुम."
NESSAROSE: Oh, they feel like they're on fire!
नेसारोज़: ओह, ऐसा लग रहा है जैसे उनमें आग लग गई हो!
-"Pede, pede, caldapess! -(rumbling, creaking)
-"पेडे, पेडे, काल्डापेस!" -(गड़गड़ाहट, चरमराहट)
-Pede, pede, caldapess!" -(screams, chuckles)
-पेडे, पेडे, काल्डापेस!" -(चीखता है, हंसता है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(gasping)
(हाँफते हुए)
(laughing)
(हँसना)
I'm floating on air.
मैं हवा में तैर रहा हूँ।
Oh, Nessa. At last.
ओह, नेसा। आखिरकार!
♪ I'd always been unsure I could ♪
♪ मुझे हमेशा से ही इस बात का संदेह था कि मैं ऐसा कर पाऊँगी ♪
♪ But finally, from these powers ♪
♪ लेकिन अंततः, इन शक्तियों से ♪
-♪ Something good ♪ -(laughing)
-♪ कुछ अच्छा ♪ -(हंसते हुए)
Finally.
अंत में।
♪ Something good ♪
♪ कुछ अच्छा ♪
Thank you, Elphaba.
धन्यवाद, एल्फाबा।
BOQ: Nessa?
बीओक्यू: नेसा?
He called me Nessa. It's working.
उन्होंने मुझे नेसा कहकर बुलाया। यह तरीका काम कर रहा है।
Nessa, there's something I have to...
नेसा, मुझे कुछ काम करना है...
Look.
देखना।
You.
आप।
-Boq. -Stay back!
-बोक। -पीछे हटो!
It's just me. I'm not gonna hurt you.
मैं अकेला हूँ। मैं तुम्हें नुकसान नहीं पहुँचाऊँगा।
NESSAROSE: Boq, don't be afraid.
नेसारोज़: बोक, डरो मत।
Elphaba just came to lift my spirits.
एल्फाबा मेरा मनोबल बढ़ाने के लिए आई थी।
You did this to make her happy?
आपने उसे खुश करने के लिए ऐसा किया?
NESSAROSE: I know now anything is possible
नेसारोज़: अब मुझे पता है कि कुछ भी संभव है।
for both of us.
हम दोनों के लिए।
-♪ Nessa? ♪ -Yes?
-♪ नेसा? ♪ -हाँ?
♪ Uh, Nessa, surely now ♪
♪ उह, नेसा, अब तो ज़रूर ♪
♪ I'll matter less to you ♪
♪ मैं तुम्हारे लिए कम महत्वपूर्ण हो जाऊँगा ♪
♪ And you won't mind my leaving here tonight ♪
♪ और आज रात मेरे यहाँ से चले जाने पर आपको कोई आपत्ति नहीं होगी ♪
Leaving?
जा रहे हो?
♪ The moment when I read ♪
♪ वो क्षण जब मैंने पढ़ा ♪
♪ Glinda's going to be wed ♪
♪ ग्लिंडा की शादी होने वाली है ♪
♪ To Fiyero ♪
♪ फियेरो को ♪
Glinda?
ग्लिंडा?
♪ Yes, Nessa, that's right ♪
♪ हां, नेसा, बिल्कुल सही ♪
♪ And I've got to go appeal to her ♪
♪ और मुझे उससे विनती करनी होगी ♪
♪ Express the way I feel to her ♪
♪ मैं उसे अपने दिल की बात बता दूँ ♪
Nessa.
के कारण से।
I lost my heart to Glinda the moment I first saw her.
ग्लिंडा को पहली बार देखते ही मैं उस पर मोहित हो गया था ।
Lost your heart?
क्या तुमने अपना दिल खो दिया?
We'll see about that.
हम उसके बारे में देखेंगे।
-Let him go. -Don't come any closer!
उसे जाने दो। उसके और करीब मत आओ!
You and your sister.
आप और आपकी बहन।
She's as Wicked as you are,
वह भी तुम्हारी ही तरह दुष्ट है।
keeping me here like a prisoner.
मुझे यहाँ कैदी की तरह रखा गया है।
What are you talking about?
तुम किस बारे में बात कर रहे हो?
I am talking about my life!
मैं अपनी जिंदगी के बारे में बात कर रहा हूँ!
The little that's left of it.
उसका जो थोड़ा-बहुत हिस्सा बचा है।
NESSAROSE: You're going to lose your heart to me, I tell you!
नेसारोज़: मैं तुम्हें बता रही हूँ, तुम मुझ पर अपना दिल हार बैठोगे !
If I have to...
अगर मुझे करना पड़े तो...
I have to...
मुझे करना होगा...
...magic spell you.
...जादुई मंत्र तुम पर लागू होता है।
There must be a magic spell in here to capture your heart.
यहां जरूर कोई जादुई मंत्र होगा जो तुम्हारा दिल जीत लेगा।
-Nessa, no. That's dangerous. -What is she doing?
-नेसा, नहीं। यह खतरनाक है। -वह क्या कर रही है?
"Ah tum, ta tayk..."
"अरे तुम, बस इतना ही..."
-Stop, Nessa! -"...ah tum, cortum."
-रुको, नेसा! -"...आह तुम, कॉर्टम."
You're pronouncing the words all wrong!
आप शब्दों का उच्चारण बिल्कुल गलत कर रहे हैं!
-Wh-What is she saying? -"Ah tum, ta tayk."
वह क्या कह रही है? -"आह तुम, ता तायक."
-I'm going. -(soft whooshing)
मैं जा रहा हूँ। (हल्की सरसराहट की आवाज़)
-NESSAROSE: "Ah tum." -(sharp whoosh)
-नेसारोज़: "आह तुम." -(तेज़ सरसराहट)
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
-(creaking) -(groaning)
(चरमराहट) (कराहना)
-Boq, what is it? -(panting)
-बोक, क्या बात है? (हाँफते हुए)
(groans) My heart.
(कराहते हुए) मेरा दिल।
(heart beating and creaking)
(दिल धड़क रहा है और चरमरा रहा है)
It feels like it's sh-- like it's shrinking.
ऐसा लगता है जैसे यह सिकुड़ रहा है।
-Do something! -ELPHABA: I can't!
-कुछ करो! -एल्फाबा: मैं नहीं कर सकती!
A spell from the Grimmerie can never be reversed.
ग्रिमेरी से किया गया कोई भी मंत्र कभी भी उलटा नहीं जा सकता।
NESSAROSE: Boq? This is all your fault!
नेसारोज़: बोक? यह सब तुम्हारी गलती है!
-If you hadn't come here... -I have to find another spell.
-अगर तुम यहाँ नहीं आते... -मुझे कोई दूसरा मंत्र ढूंढना पड़ेगा।
It's the only thing that might work.
यही एक तरीका है जिससे शायद काम बन सकता है।
Go, now! Go!
जाओ, अभी जाओ! जाओ!
(pained groaning)
(दर्द भरी कराह)
(heartbeat continues faster)
(दिल की धड़कन तेज होती जा रही है)
♪ Save him, please, just save him ♪
♪ उसे बचाओ, कृपया, बस उसे बचा लो ♪
-♪ My poor Boq, my sweet ♪ -"Ambulahn dasca."
-♪ मेरे बेचारे बोक, मेरे प्यारे ♪ -"अम्बुलाहन दासका."
♪ My brave him ♪
♪ मेरा बहादुर वह ♪
-♪ Don't leave me till ♪ -"Lahfenahto."
-♪ मुझे तब तक मत छोड़ो ♪ -"लाहफेनाहतो."
♪ My sorry life has ceased ♪
♪ मेरा दुख भरा जीवन समाप्त हो गया ♪
-"Caldapess." -(groans)
-"काल्डापेस." -(करहाता है)
♪ Alone and loveless here ♪
♪ मैं यहाँ अकेला और प्रेमहीन हूँ ♪
♪ With just the girl in the mirror ♪
♪ केवल आईने में दिख रही लड़की के साथ ♪
♪ Just her and me ♪
♪ बस वो और मैं ♪
♪ The Wicked Witch of the East ♪
♪ पूरब की दुष्ट चुड़ैल ♪
-(Boq groans) -(metal clicking)
(बोक कराहता है) (धातु के टकराने की आवाज़)
♪ We deserve each other. ♪
♪ हम एक दूसरे के लायक हैं। ♪
(door closes)
(दरवाजा बंद हो जाता है)
He's sleeping now.
वह अभी सो रहा है।
What about his heart?
उसके दिल का क्या हुआ?
It's all right.
ठीक ठाक है।
He won't need one now.
अब उसे इसकी जरूरत नहीं पड़ेगी।
The wedding.
शादी।
Wait, where are you going?
रुको, तुम कहाँ जा रहे हो?
All the most influential people in Oz will be there.
ऑस्ट्रेलिया के सभी सबसे प्रभावशाली लोग वहां मौजूद होंगे।
It's the perfect opportunity to show them all the truth
उन्हें सारी सच्चाई दिखाने का यह बिल्कुल सही मौका है ।
about the Wizard.
जादूगर के बारे में।
Oh, please. Stop lying to yourself.
अरे, प्लीज़। खुद से झूठ बोलना बंद करो।
You're going there to find Fiyero, but it's too late.
आप वहां फियेरो को ढूंढने जा रहे हैं , लेकिन बहुत देर हो चुकी है।
Nessa, I have done everything I could for you,
नेसा, मैंने तुम्हारे लिए हर संभव प्रयास किया है।
and it hasn't been enough.
और यह पर्याप्त नहीं रहा है।
Nothing ever will be.
कुछ भी कभी नहीं होगा।
Elphaba, don't leave me!
एल्फाबा, मुझे छोड़कर मत जाओ!
Goodbye, Nessa.
अलविदा, नेसा।
I'm off to see the Wizard.
मैं जादूगर से मिलने जा रहा हूँ।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
-(clattering in other room) -(Boq groaning)
(दूसरे कमरे में खड़खड़ाहट की आवाज़) (बोक के कराहने की आवाज़)
BOQ: Where am I?
बीओक्यू: मैं कहाँ हूँ?
What happened?
क्या हुआ?
(chuckles) It's all right, dearest.
(हंसते हुए) कोई बात नहीं, प्रियतम।
You just...
आप बस...
-(banging on door) -(Boq grunting)
(दरवाजे पर जोर से दस्तक) (बोक की गुर्राहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(footsteps clanking)
(पैरों की खनखनाहट)
What have you done?
क्या कर डाले?
It wasn't me.
यह मैंने नहीं किया था।
I tried to stop her.
मैंने उसे रोकने की कोशिश की।
(metal squeaking)
(धातु की चरमराहट)
Boq, please.
बोक, कृपया।
(breathing heavily)
(तेजी से सांस लेते हुए)
What have you done to me?
आपने मेरे लिए क्या किया है?
You witch!
तुम चुड़ैल हो!
It wasn't me! It was her!
ये मैं नहीं था! ये वो थी!
It was Elphaba!
यह एल्फाबा थी!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
(breathing shakily)
(कांपती हुई सांसों के साथ)
Boq!
बगीचा!
MADAME MORRIBLE (amplified): Ozians of the Emerald City,
मैडम मॉरिबल (विस्तारित): एमराल्ड सिटी के ओज़ियन,
today the winds shift
आज हवाओं का रुख बदल गया है
and destiny unfolds before our very eyes...
और नियति हमारी आंखों के सामने खुलती है...
-THE WIZARD: Mm-hmm. -...for on this night,
-जादूगर: हम्म-हम्म... क्योंकि आज रात,
by the glorification of our Wizard,
हमारे जादूगर की महिमा के द्वारा ,
Glinda the Good and Prince Fiyero Tigelaar
ग्लिंडा द गुड और प्रिंस फ़िएरो टिगेलार
join hands in unification.
एकजुटता के लिए हाथ मिलाओ।
Do I have everything I need?
क्या मेरे पास वह सब कुछ है जिसकी मुझे जरूरत है?
No, I need an earring, please.
नहीं, मुझे एक बाली चाहिए, कृपया।
-Thank you. -(chittering)
-धन्यवाद। (चहचहाते हुए)
Something oldish? Yes.
कुछ पुराना? हाँ।
MADAME MORRIBLE: This is more than just a wedding.
मैडम मॉरिबल: यह सिर्फ एक शादी से कहीं अधिक है।
It is a coronation of hope itself.
यह तो आशा का ही राज्याभिषेक है ।
(gears cranking)
(गियर घूमने की आवाज़)
GLINDA: Something new?
ग्लिंडा: कुछ नया?
(chuckles) Absolutely.
(हंसते हुए) बिलकुल।
MADAME MORRIBLE: So let the very foundations
मैडम मॉरिबल: तो फिर बुनियाद ही...
of Oz shimmer with celebratorium...
ऑस्ट्रेलिया उत्सवों की चमक से जगमगा रहा है...
-(excited chatter) -Let's go!
(उत्साह से भरी बातचीत) -चलो चलें!
...for today, Oz writes a new chapter.
...आज के लिए, ओज़ एक नया अध्याय लिख रहे हैं।
Rejoicify,
आनंद मनाओ,
and Oz shall shine forevermore.
और ओज़ हमेशा के लिए चमकता रहेगा।
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
(Glinda chuckles)
(ग्लिंडा हंसती है)
GLINDA: Something bartered.
ग्लिंडा: कुछ अदला-बदली की गई।
And something askew. I need something askew.
और कुछ टेढ़ा-मेढ़ा। मुझे कुछ टेढ़ा-मेढ़ा चाहिए।
-(bang on door) -(gasps)
(दरवाजे पर ज़ोर से दस्तक) (हैरान होकर)
(glass tinkling and crackling)
(कांच की खनक और चटकने की आवाज)
Just give me a clock-tick.
बस मुझे एक घड़ी की टिक-टिक बता दीजिए।
Elphaba Thropp, I know you're out here.
एल्फाबा थ्रोप, मुझे पता है तुम यहीं हो।
Just come in before the monkeys spot you.
बंदरों की नजर पड़ने से पहले ही अंदर आ जाओ ।
(Glinda gasps)
(ग्लिंडा हांफती है)
Elphaba.
एल्फाबा।
Galinda.
गलिंडा।
Get in. Go.
अंदर आओ। जाओ।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Elphie.
एल्फी।
Thank Oz you're alive.
भगवान का शुक्र है कि तुम जिंदा हो।
Careful. Your dress.
सावधान। आपकी पोशाक।
I still can't believe you get around on that old thing.
मुझे अब भी विश्वास नहीं हो रहा कि तुम उस पुरानी चीज पर घूमते हो।
Well, we can't all come and go by bubble.
खैर, हम सभी बुलबुले के जरिए आ-जा नहीं सकते ।
True.
सत्य।
(chuckles softly)
(हल्की सी हंसी)
Are you all right?
तुम ठीक हो?
I'm fine.
मैं ठीक हूँ।
I just wanted to come and see you.
मैं बस आपसे मिलने आया था।
That means a lot to me, Elphie.
एल्फी, यह मेरे लिए बहुत मायने रखता है।
But if anyone discoverates you...
लेकिन अगर कोई आपको खोज ले तो...
I know. I know.
मैं जानता हूँ मुझे पता है।
You never saw me.
तुमने मुझे कभी नहीं देखा।
I was never here. Do you understand?
मैं यहाँ कभी था ही नहीं। क्या आप समझते हैं?
No. I can't bear this anymore.
नहीं। मैं इसे और बर्दाश्त नहीं कर सकता।
I'm taking you to see the Wizard.
मैं तुम्हें जादूगर से मिलवाने ले जा रहा हूँ।
Absolutely not.
कदापि नहीं।
-Yes. -No!
-हां नहीं!
This is between the Wizard and I.
यह मामला जादूगर और मेरे बीच का है।
(sighs) I understand. But you have to trust me.
(आह भरते हुए) मैं समझती हूँ। लेकिन आपको मुझ पर भरोसा करना होगा।
I know how to talk to him,
मुझे पता है उससे कैसे बात करनी है।
-and maybe I could help work something out. -(whooshing)
और शायद मैं कुछ हल निकालने में मदद कर सकूँ। (तेजी से आवाज़ करते हुए)
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(The Wizard scatting)
(जादूगर की मधुर धुन)
(chuckling)
(हंसते हुए)
(scatting)
(स्कैटिंग)
-(model train whistle blows) -♪ Since I've... ♪
(मॉडल ट्रेन की सीटी बजती है) -♪ जब से मैंने... ♪
-(bell dings) -(scatting)
(घंटी बजती है) (स्कैटिंग)
What?
क्या?
(soft whoosh)
(हल्की सरसराहट)
(The Wizard scatting)
(जादूगर की मधुर धुन)
-(whistle blows) -(model train chugging)
(सीटी बजती है) (मॉडल ट्रेन की आवाज)
-(scatting) -(gears rattling and clanking)
(बहस की आवाज़) (गियरों की खड़खड़ाहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(whistle blows)
(सीटी बजती है)
(jingling)
(झनझनाहट)
ELPHABA: You're done.
एल्फाबा: आपका काम हो गया।
It's over.
सब खत्म हो गया।
I had a hunch you'd be coming back to me.
मुझे पहले से ही अंदाजा था कि तुम मेरे पास वापस आओगे।
I'm not here for you. I'm here for Oz.
मैं तुम्हारे लिए यहाँ नहीं हूँ। मैं ओज़ के लिए यहाँ हूँ।
GLINDA: Elphaba.
ग्लिंडा: एल्फाबा।
You know, you could've just exited normally.
आप जानते हैं, आप सामान्य तरीके से बाहर निकल सकते थे।
Just use the door.
बस दरवाजे का इस्तेमाल करें।
Hello?
नमस्ते?
-ELPHABA: (sighs) Yes? -Don't hate me.
-एल्फाबा: (आह भरते हुए) हाँ? -मुझसे नफरत मत करो।
It's my wedding day,
आज मेरी शादी का दिन है।
and you cannot refuse a wedding wish.
और आप शादी की इच्छा को अस्वीकार नहीं कर सकते।
Well, you can, but it's rude.
वैसे तो आप कर सकते हैं, लेकिन यह असभ्य होगा।
ELPHABA: I don't have time for this. Now, listen.
एल्फाबा: मेरे पास इसके लिए समय नहीं है । अब, सुनो।
You and I are gonna go down there together,
हम दोनों साथ-साथ वहाँ जाएँगे।
and you are gonna admit to her guests
और तुम उसके मेहमानों के सामने यह बात स्वीकार करने वाले हो।
that you have no real power
कि आपके पास कोई वास्तविक शक्ति नहीं है
and that you cannot read the Grimmerie.
और आप ग्रिमेरी नहीं पढ़ सकते।
(laughing)
(हँसना)
Why is that funny?
क्यों है वह मज़ेदार?
Elphaba, uh, I've missed you.
एल्फाबा, उह, मुझे तुम्हारी बहुत याद आई।
(sighs) Can't we start again?
(आह भरते हुए) क्या हम फिर से शुरुआत नहीं कर सकते?
Yes. Please.
जी कहिये।
-Just say yes. -No.
-बस हाँ कह दो। -नहीं।
Don't you think I wish I could?
क्या आपको नहीं लगता कि मैं ऐसा करना चाहता हूँ?
I would give anything to go back to a time when I...
मैं उस समय में वापस जाने के लिए कुछ भी देने को तैयार हूँ जब मैं...
...when I actually believed that you were Wonderful.
...जब मुझे सचमुच विश्वास था कि आप अद्भुत हैं।
"The Wonderful Wizard of Oz."
"ऑस्ट्रेलिया का हैरत अंगेज विज़ार्ड।"
No one believed in you more than I did.
मुझसे ज्यादा तुम पर किसी को भरोसा नहीं था ।
But there's no going back.
लेकिन अब पीछे मुड़ने का कोई रास्ता नहीं है।
And we can't move forward,
और हम आगे नहीं बढ़ सकते।
not until everyone knows what I know.
जब तक सबको वह बात पता न चल जाए जो मुझे पता है, तब तक नहीं।
And once they know the truth...
और एक बार जब उन्हें सच्चाई पता चल जाएगी...
They're not gonna believe it.
उन्हें इस पर विश्वास नहीं होगा।
How can you say that?
आप इसे कैसे कहेंगे?
Well, I'm just being straight with you.
ठीक है, मैं आपसे सीधे-सीधे बात कर रहा हूँ।
I could tell 'em that I'd been lying to 'em
मैं उन्हें बता सकता था कि मैं उनसे झूठ बोल रहा था।
till I'm-- forgive me-- blue in the face,
जब तक मैं— मुझे माफ करना— पूरी तरह थक न जाऊं,
but wouldn't make any difference.
लेकिन इससे कोई फर्क नहीं पड़ेगा ।
They're never gonna stop believing in me.
वे मुझ पर विश्वास करना कभी नहीं छोड़ेंगे ।
You know why?
तुम जानते हो क्यों?
Because they don't want to.
क्योंकि वे ऐसा नहीं करना चाहते।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Take it from a wise, old carny ♪
♪ एक अनुभवी, समझदार सर्कस वाले की बात मानिए ♪
♪ Once folks buy into your blarney ♪
♪ एक बार जब लोग आपकी मीठी बातों पर विश्वास कर लेते हैं ♪
♪ It becomes the thing they'll most hold on to ♪
♪ यही वो चीज़ बन जाती है जिसे वे सबसे ज़्यादा थामे रखेंगे ♪
♪ Once they've swallowed sham and hokum ♪
♪ जब वे पाखंड और धोखे को निगल चुके हों ♪
♪ Facts and logic won't unchoke 'em ♪
♪ तथ्य और तर्क उन्हें शांत नहीं कर पाएंगे ♪
♪ They'll go on believing what they want to ♪
♪ वे वही मानते रहेंगे जो वे मानना ​​चाहते हैं ♪
♪ Show them exactly what's the score ♪
♪ उन्हें ठीक-ठीक स्थिति दिखाओ ♪
(Glinda chuckles)
(ग्लिंडा हंसती है)
♪ They'll just believe it even more ♪
♪ वे इस पर और भी अधिक विश्वास करने लगेंगे ♪
(softly): Watch this.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): इसे देखो।
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
♪ Wonderful ♪
♪ शानदार ♪
♪ They called me Wonderful ♪
♪ उन्होंने मुझे अद्भुत कहा ♪
♪ So I said ♪
♪ तो मैंने कहा ♪
♪ "Wonderful? If you insist" ♪
♪ "शानदार? अगर आप ज़िद करते हैं तो" ♪
(Glinda gasps, chuckles)
(ग्लिंडा हांफती है, हंसती है)
♪ Wonderful ♪
♪ शानदार ♪
♪ I will be Wonderful ♪
♪ मैं अद्भुत बनूंगा ♪
♪ Believe me, it's hard to resist ♪
♪ यकीन मानिए, इसका विरोध करना मुश्किल है ♪
♪ 'Cause it feels Wonderful ♪
♪ क्योंकि यह बहुत अच्छा लगता है ♪
♪ They think he's Wonderful ♪
♪ वे उसे अद्भुत मानते हैं ♪
♪ Hey, look who's Wonderful ♪
♪ अरे, देखो कौन है अद्भुत ♪
♪ This corn-fed hick ♪
♪ यह देहाती लड़का ♪
♪ Who said, "It might be keen ♪
♪ किसने कहा, "यह दिलचस्प हो सकता है ♪
♪ "To build a town of green ♪
♪ "हरियाली का शहर बसाने के लिए ♪"
♪ And a wonderful road of yellow brick" ♪
♪ और पीली ईंटों की एक अद्भुत सड़क ♪
Ow!
ओह!
(The Wizard chuckling)
(जादूगर खिलखिलाकर हंसता है)
Bee-keek, beak-beak.
बी-कीक, बीक-बीक।
(chuckles)
(हंसते हुए)
Elphie, let's be honest.
एल्फी, चलो ईमानदार रहें।
Your way hasn't worked.
आपका तरीका कारगर नहीं रहा।
But if you join forces with us,
लेकिन अगर आप हमारे साथ जुड़ते हैं,
if people see that you're with us, they'll begin to trust you.
अगर लोगों को यह दिखेगा कि आप हमारे साथ हैं, तो वे आप पर भरोसा करने लगेंगे।
You'll accomplish so much more.
आप इससे कहीं अधिक उपलब्धियां हासिल करेंगे।
Yeah, yeah. So much more.
हाँ, हाँ। और भी बहुत कुछ।
You know, we could be like a... like a family.
आप जानते हैं, हम एक परिवार की तरह हो सकते हैं।
You know, I've never really had a family.
आप जानते हैं, मेरा कभी कोई परिवार नहीं रहा।
Lucky you.
बहुत भाग्यशाली हो।
That's why I've wanted to give the citizens of Oz...
इसीलिए मैं ओज़ के नागरिकों को यह देना चाहता था...
everything.
सब कुछ।
-So you lied to them? -No.
-तो क्या तुमने उनसे झूठ बोला? -नहीं।
No.
नहीं।
No-- Well, um...
नहीं-- खैर, उम...
only v-verbally.
केवल मौखिक रूप से।
But those were the lies that they wanted to hear.
लेकिन वे वही झूठ थे जो वे सुनना चाहते थे।
♪ The truth is not a thing of fact or reason ♪
♪ सत्य तथ्य या तर्क की वस्तु नहीं है ♪
♪ The truth is just what everyone agrees on ♪
♪ सच्चाई वही है जिस पर सभी सहमत हों ♪
You see, back where I come from,
देखिए, जहां से मैं आया हूँ,
we got a whole lot of people who believe
हमारे पास बहुत सारे लोग हैं जो मानते हैं
all sorts of things that aren't true.
ऐसी कई बातें जो सच नहीं हैं।
You know what we call it?
आप जानते हैं हम इसे क्या कहते हैं?
History.
इतिहास।
Ooh.
ओह।
-♪ A man's called a traitor ♪ -(bell dings)
-♪ एक आदमी को गद्दार कहा जाता है ♪ -(घंटी बजती है)
♪ Or liberator ♪
♪ या मुक्तिदाता ♪
♪ A rich man's a thief ♪
♪ एक अमीर आदमी चोर होता है ♪
♪ Or philanthropist ♪
♪ या परोपकारी ♪
♪ Is one an invader ♪
♪ क्या कोई आक्रमणकारी है ♪
♪ Or noble crusader? ♪
♪ या फिर कोई महान धर्मयोद्धा? ♪
♪ It's all in which label is able to persist ♪
♪ यह सब इस बात पर निर्भर करता है कि कौन सा लेबल लंबे समय तक कायम रह पाता है ♪
♪ There are precious few at ease ♪
♪ बहुत कम लोग ही आराम से हैं ♪
♪ With moral ambiguities ♪
♪ नैतिक अस्पष्टताओं के साथ ♪
♪ So we act as though they don't exist ♪
♪ इसलिए हम ऐसा व्यवहार करते हैं मानो वे मौजूद ही न हों ♪
It's not my best pupil.
यह मेरा सबसे अच्छा छात्र नहीं है।
♪ They call him Wonderful ♪
♪ वे उसे अद्भुत कहते हैं ♪
♪ So I am Wonderful ♪
♪ इसलिए मैं अद्भुत हूँ ♪
♪ He is so Wonderful ♪
♪ वह बहुत अद्भुत है ♪
♪ It's part of his name ♪
♪ यह उनके नाम का हिस्सा है ♪
♪ And with our help, you can be the same ♪
♪ और हमारी मदद से आप भी वैसे ही बन सकते हैं ♪
GLINDA: Come with me.
ग्लिंडा: मेरे साथ आओ।
Elphie, aren't you tired of running?
एल्फी, क्या तुम दौड़ते-दौड़ते थक नहीं गई हो?
Think of what we could do.
सोचो हम क्या कर सकते हैं।
Together.
एक साथ।
♪ Unlimited ♪
♪ असीमित ♪
♪ Together we're unlimited ♪
♪ साथ मिलकर हम असीमित हैं ♪
♪ Together we'll be ♪
♪ हम साथ रहेंगे ♪
♪ The greatest team there's ever been ♪
♪ अब तक की सबसे महान टीम ♪
♪ Elphie ♪
♪ एल्फी ♪
♪ Dreams the way we planned 'em ♪
♪ सपने, जैसे हमने योजना बनाई थी ♪
(Glinda giggles)
(ग्लिंडा खिलखिलाती है)
♪ If we work in tandem ♪
♪ अगर हम मिलकर काम करें ♪
♪ There's no fight we cannot win ♪
♪ ऐसा कोई युद्ध नहीं जिसे हम जीत न सकें ♪
♪ At long, long last, receive your due ♪
♪ आखिरकार, तुम्हें तुम्हारा हक मिल ही गया ♪
♪ Long overdue ♪
♪ बहुत समय से प्रतीक्षित ♪
♪ Elphaba, a celebration throughout Oz ♪
♪ एल्फाबा, पूरे ओज़ में एक उत्सव ♪
♪ That's all to do ♪
♪ बस इतना ही करना है ♪
♪ With you ♪
♪ तुम्हारे साथ ♪
(Glinda and The Wizard chuckling)
(ग्लिंडा और जादूगर हंसते हैं)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Wonderful ♪
♪ शानदार ♪
♪ They'll call you Wonderful ♪
♪ वे तुम्हें अद्भुत कहेंगे ♪
♪ Come and be Wonderful ♪
♪ आओ और अद्भुत बनो ♪
THE WIZARD: ♪ Trust me, it's fun ♪
जादूगर: ♪ मेरा विश्वास करो, यह मजेदार है ♪
-♪ We will be Wonderful ♪ -(laughing)
-♪ हम शानदार होंगे ♪ -(हंसते हुए)
-♪ You'll make me Wonderful ♪ -(squeals)
-♪ तुम मुझे अद्भुत बना दोगे ♪ -(चीखती है)
♪ Wonderful, Wonderful ♪
♪ अद्भुत, अद्भुत ♪
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(Elphaba and Glinda chuckling)
(एल्फाबा और ग्लिंडा हंसती हैं)
(Glinda squeals)
(ग्लिंडा चीखती है)
(growling)
(गुर्राते हुए)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(deep, grating voice): Who are you?
(गहरी, कर्कश आवाज): तुम कौन हो?
And why do you seek me?
और तुम मुझे क्यों ढूंढ रहे हो?
Wait.
इंतज़ार।
(music stops)
(संगीत बंद हो जाता है)
♪ It's possible I could agree ♪
♪ हो सकता है मैं सहमत हो जाऊं ♪
♪ Wonderful ♪
♪ शानदार ♪
♪ But this time ♪
♪ लेकिन इस बार ♪
♪ You have to prove yourself to me ♪
♪ तुम्हें खुद को मेरे सामने साबित करना होगा ♪
No more blaming the animals.
अब जानवरों को दोष देना बंद करो।
And the ones who've left Oz should be
और जो लोग ऑस्ट्रेलिया छोड़ चुके हैं, उन्हें ऐसा करना चाहिए।
free to return without fear.
बिना किसी डर के वापस लौटने के लिए स्वतंत्र।
THE WIZARD: Hey, with you by my side,
जादूगर: अरे, तुम्हारे साथ होने से,
I'm not gonna need to blame the animals anymore.
अब मुझे जानवरों को दोष देने की जरूरत नहीं पड़ेगी।
You're not gonna need spies, either,
आपको जासूसों की भी जरूरत नहीं पड़ेगी।
so set the monkeys free.
इसलिए बंदरों को मुक्त कर दो।
(softly): Oh, yeah? Hang on. Hang on.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): ओह, हाँ? ज़रा रुकिए। ज़रा रुकिए।
(The Wizard sighs heavily)
(जादूगर गहरी आह भरता है)
Why? Why?
क्यों? क्यों?
I think I got it.
मुझे लगता है मुझे समझ आ गया।
Um...
एक...
Done.
हो गया।
GLINDA: (gasps) I did it.
ग्लिंडा: (हैरान होकर) मैंने कर दिखाया।
I mean, we did it.
मतलब, हमने कर दिखाया।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
I'll see you two in a clock-tick.
मैं आप दोनों से कुछ ही देर में मिलूंगा ।
Elphie, I'm so happy.
एल्फी, मैं बहुत खुश हूँ।
-(giggles) -(chuckles)
(हंसते हुए) (मुस्कुराते हुए)
(giggles) I'm getting married.
(हंसते हुए) मेरी शादी हो रही है।
(squeals)
(चीखती है)
So, you want me to prove myself?
तो, आप चाहते हैं कि मैं खुद को साबित करूं?
Oh, my gosh.
ओह, मेरे भगवान।
Look in your hand.
अपने हाथ में देखो।
How'd that get there?
वह वहां कैसे पहुंचा?
It's a key. It's a key.
यह एक चाबी है। यह एक चाबी है।
(laughing)
(हँसना)
(laughing): Aren't you surprised?
(हंसते हुए): क्या आपको आश्चर्य नहीं हुआ?
I liked that dance. That was fun. Come here.
मुझे वो डांस अच्छा लगा। बहुत मज़ा आया। इधर आओ।
Now, (clears throat) I've been keeping them
अब, (गला साफ़ करते हुए) मैं उन्हें रख रहा हूँ
locked in here, um, for their own safety.
इन्हें यहाँ बंद कर दिया गया है, उनकी अपनी सुरक्षा के लिए।
(monkeys chattering)
(बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
But, ah, no need for that anymore.
लेकिन, अब इसकी कोई जरूरत नहीं है।
Okay.
ठीक है।
Hey, you want to come over here and do the honors?
हे, क्या आप इधर आकर यह कार्य करना चाहेंगे ?
Uh, 'cause if you put that in-in here, it'll let 'em go.
अह, क्योंकि अगर आप इसे यहाँ डालेंगे, तो यह उन्हें जाने देगा।
And, uh, I...
और, उह, मैं...
Gosh, I-I hope you feel good about this whole thing, 'cause,
हे भगवान, मुझे उम्मीद है कि आपको इस सब से अच्छा लग रहा होगा, क्योंकि...
well, you've won, but I think we all have.
खैर, आप जीत गए, लेकिन मुझे लगता है कि हम सभी जीत गए हैं।
-(heavy creaking) -(monkeys chattering)
(तेज़ चरमराहट की आवाज़) (बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
(chattering intensifies)
(बकवास तेज हो जाती है)
Chistery.
चिस्टरी।
(gruff breathing)
(तेज साँस लेना)
Nothing can change what's been done to you.
जो कुछ आपके साथ हो चुका है, उसे कोई नहीं बदल सकता ।
Well... what I've done.
अच्छा... मैंने क्या किया है।
But at least you have your freedom now.
लेकिन कम से कम अब आपके पास आजादी तो है।
-Chistery, can you speak? -(grunts)
-चिस्टरी, क्या तुम बोल सकते हो? -(घुरघुराहट)
Please try.
प्रयास करें।
Well... go on.
अच्छा... आगे बढ़ो।
You're free.
आप स्वतंत्र हैं।
Fly.
उड़ना।
(screeching)
(चीखते हुए)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
Fly.
उड़ना।
Fly!
उड़ना!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Wonderful. Uh...
बहुत बढ़िया। उह...
Well...
कुंआ...
Hey, if you and I are gonna go down there
अरे, अगर हम दोनों वहाँ जाने वाले हैं
and greet those fancy folks, I'd better, uh, spruce up.
और उन प्रतिष्ठित लोगों का अभिवादन करने के लिए, मुझे बेहतर होगा कि मैं, उह, थोड़ा सज-धज कर तैयार हो जाऊं।
(chuckling)
(हंसते हुए)
Chistery, what's wrong?
चिस्टरी, क्या हुआ?
(heavy rumble)
(तेज गड़गड़ाहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(quiet murmuring)
(धीमी फुसफुसाहट)
(instruments playing gentle music)
( मधुर संगीत बजाने वाले वाद्य यंत्र)
(Ozians whispering, gasping)
(ओज़ियन फुसफुसा रहे हैं, हांफ रहे हैं)
(gentle music continues)
(मधुर संगीत जारी है)
(animals murmuring)
(जानवरों की गुर्राहट)
-(animals clamoring) -(bars and chains rattling)
(जानवरों का शोर) (सलाखों और जंजीरों की खड़खड़ाहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(animals clamoring)
(जानवरों का शोर)
(clamoring continues)
(शोर-शराबा जारी है)
(applause)
(तालियाँ)
(both chuckle softly)
(दोनों धीरे से हंसते हैं)
(clamoring continues)
(शोर-शराबा जारी है)
Dr. Dillamond.
डॉ. डिलमंड।
Can't you speak?
क्या आप बोल नहीं सकते?
It's me, Elphaba.
मैं हूं, एल्फाबा।
(bleating)
(मिमियाना)
THE WIZARD: Let me explain, 'cause th--
जादूगर: मुझे समझाने दीजिए, क्योंकि...
this is not what it looks like.
यह वैसा नहीं है जैसा दिख रहा है।
-(animals clamoring) -(bars and chains rattling)
(जानवरों का शोर) (सलाखों और जंजीरों की खड़खड़ाहट)
Elphaba, some animals cannot be trusted.
एल्फाबा, कुछ जानवरों पर भरोसा नहीं किया जा सकता।
Yes.
हाँ।
I know that now.
अब मुझे यह पता चल गया है।
(clamoring continues)
(शोर-शराबा जारी है)
And these sacred vows
और ये पवित्र प्रतिज्ञाएँ
-are to be entered into -(distant clamoring)
-प्रवेश किया जाना है -(दूर से आ रही कोलाहल की आवाज)
not lightly but merrily.
हल्के में नहीं, बल्कि खुशी-खुशी।
Elphaba, try to understand.
एल्फाबा, समझने की कोशिश करो।
No.
नहीं।
I'm not a bad man. I'm just a...
मैं बुरा आदमी नहीं हूँ। मैं बस एक...
Yes, you are. You're a very bad man.
हाँ, तुम हो। तुम बहुत बुरे आदमी हो।
(clamoring and rattling growing louder)
(शोर और खड़खड़ाहट तेज होती जा रही है)
You once asked me what my heart's desire was,
आपने एक बार मुझसे पूछा था कि मेरे दिल की ख्वाहिश क्या है,
and I know now what that is.
और अब मुझे पता है कि वह क्या है।
And that is to fight you till the day I die!
और वो यह है कि मैं अपनी मृत्यु तक तुमसे लड़ूंगा !
-(locks snapping) -(The Wizard grunts)
(ताले टूटने की आवाज) (जादूगर कराहता है)
(growling)
(गुर्राते हुए)
-(breathing heavily) -(clamoring quiets)
(तेजी से सांस लेते हुए) (शोरगुल शांत हो जाता है)
Run.
दौड़ना।
-(animals clamoring wildly) -(birds squawking)
(जानवरों का शोरगुल) (पक्षियों का चहचहाना)
(grunting)
(घुरघुराहट)
Wha-- (grunting)
क्या-- (घुरघुराहट)
And do you, Glinda...
और क्या तुम, ग्लिंडा...
-(distant clamoring) -(Ozians murmuring)
(दूर से आती हुई कोलाहल की आवाज) (ओज़ियनों की बड़बड़ाहट)
What is that horrendible sound?
यह भयानक आवाज कैसी है?
-(screaming) -(animals clamoring wildly)
(चीखने की आवाज़) (जानवरों का बेतहाशा शोर मचाना)
-(gasps) -(Ozians screaming)
(सांस फूलना) (ओज़ियन चीख रहे हैं)
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
-(gasps) -Move!
(सांस फूलते हुए) - हटो!
(clamoring and screaming continue)
(शोर-शराबा और चीख-पुकार जारी है)
Stay there.
वहाँ रहें।
-(grunting) -(screaming)
(घुरघुराहट) (चीखना)
Fiyero!
फियेरो!
(whimpering)
(सिसकते हुए)
(screaming)
(चीखते हुए)
(clamoring continues)
(शोर-शराबा जारी है)
This is the work of the Wicked Witch!
यह दुष्ट चुड़ैल का काम है !
She wants to kill us all!
वह हम सबको मारना चाहती है!
(grunting)
(घुरघुराहट)
(screams)
(चीखें)
(frog croaks)
(मेंढक टर्राता है)
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
(bird calling)
(पक्षी की आवाज)
(muttering, grunting)
(बड़बड़ाते हुए, गुर्राते हुए)
No-- (groaning)
नहीं-- (कराहते हुए)
(straining)
(ज़ोर लगाते हुए)
How does it feel to have your voice taken away?
अपनी आवाज छिन जाने पर कैसा महसूस होता है ?
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
Silence, Witch!
चुप रहो, चुड़ैल!
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
Water.
पानी।
Lots of it. Bring water!
बहुत सारा। पानी साथ लाना!
GUARD: Yes, sir.
गार्ड: जी हाँ, महोदय।
As much as you can carry.
जितना आप उठा सकते हैं।
A little help? (coughs weakly)
थोड़ी मदद कर सकते हो? (कमजोर खांसी)
-Ah. (inhales sharply) -(broomstick creaking)
-आह। (तेजी से सांस लेता है) -(झाड़ू की डंडी की चरमराहट)
Please.
कृपया।
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
(sighs) Thank you.
(आह भरते हुए) धन्यवाद।
That was, uh, unpleasant.
वह, उह, अप्रिय था।
Well, I think my trachea
खैर, मुझे लगता है मेरी श्वासनली
is otherwi--
अन्यथा--
What? What are you doing?
क्या? तुम क्या कर रहे हो?
-Shush, you. Get in. -What?
-चुप रहो तुम। अंदर आओ। -क्या?
Get in.
अंदर आना।
Unless you want the guests to know
जब तक आप नहीं चाहते कि मेहमानों को पता चले
the truth about their Wizard.
उनके जादूगर के बारे में सच्चाई।
-(The Wizard groans) -Get in!
(जादूगर कराहता है) - अंदर आओ!
THE WIZARD: Yes, yes.
जादूगर: जी हाँ, जी हाँ।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Your Ozness!
आपका ओज़नेस!
Fiyero. What are you...
फियेरो। तुम क्या हो...?
What is happening?
क्या हो रहा है?
What's happened is that these two traitors...
हुआ ये है कि ये दोनों गद्दार...
Not another word, Your Ozness.
एक और शब्द नहीं, योर ओज़नेस।
Darling, have you misplaced your mind?
प्रिय, क्या तुम अपना दिमाग खो बैठी हो?
What are you doing?
आप क्या कर रहे हो?
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
I'm going with her.
मैं उसके साथ जा रहा हूँ।
-What?
-क्या?
Let's go.
चल दर।
-Let's go.
-चलो चलते हैं।
Wait. What?
किसकी प्रतीक्षा?
You mean to tell me that the two of you...
आपका मतलब यह है कि आप दोनों...
-This whole time? -No, it wasn't like that.
-क्या यह सब इतने समय से चल रहा था? -नहीं, ऐसा नहीं था।
Go.
जाना।
Now.
अब।
(Glinda crying softly)
(ग्लिंडा धीरे-धीरे रो रही है)
You deserve each other.
आप दोनों एक-दूसरे के लायक हैं।
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
ELPHABA: You frightened me.
एल्फाबा: तुमने मुझे डरा दिया।
For a while there, I thought you changed.
कुछ समय के लिए तो मुझे लगा कि तुम बदल गए हो।
I have changed.
मैं बदल गया हुँ।
This dulls the pain, if you want a swig?
इससे दर्द कम हो जाता है, अगर आप एक घूंट पीना चाहें तो?
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
(door opens)
(दरवाजा खुलता है)
No, no, no, no!
नहीं, नहीं, नहीं, नहीं!
No! No! (sighs)
नहीं! नहीं! (आह भरते हुए)
We've got the water, Madame.
हमारे पास पानी है, महोदया।
Fools! You're too late.
मूर्खों! अब बहुत देर हो चुकी है।
Get out!
चले जाओ!
How could you let this happen?
आपने ऐसा कैसे होने दिया?
THE WIZARD: Uh, do you have a hairpin?
जादूगर: उह, क्या आपके पास हेयरपिन है?
Thanks.
धन्यवाद।
Uh, she and I had a deal.
अह, मेरे और उसके बीच एक समझौता हुआ था।
But, uh...
लेकिन, उह...
she double-crossed me.
उसने मुझे धोखा दिया।
MADAME MORRIBLE: We must smoke her out,
मैडम मॉरिबल: हमें उसे बाहर निकालना होगा।
force her to show herself.
उसे खुद को दिखाने के लिए मजबूर करो।
THE WIZARD: Uh, without the monkeys,
जादूगर: उह, बंदरों के बिना,
I don't know how we're gonna do that.
मुझे नहीं पता कि हम यह कैसे करेंगे।
Her sister.
उसकी बहन।
Use her sister.
उसकी बहन का इस्तेमाल करो।
Spread a rumor that her sister's in trouble.
यह अफवाह फैला दो कि उसकी बहन मुसीबत में है।
She'll fly to her side, and you'll have her.
वह उसकी तरफ उड़कर जाएगी, और वह तुम्हें मिल जाएगी।
Now, if you'll excuse me, I need to lie down.
अब, अगर आप मुझे अनुमति दें, तो मुझे लेटना होगा।
I have a bit of a headache.
मुझे थोड़ा सिरदर्द हो रहा है।
A rumor won't do.
अफवाह से काम नहीं चलेगा।
Elphaba's too smart. That's right.
एल्फाबा बहुत होशियार है। बिल्कुल सही।
These things must be done delicately.
इन चीजों को बहुत सावधानी से करना होगा।
Perhaps...
शायद...
a change in the weather.
मौसम में बदलाव।
-(wind blowing) -(objects tinkling)
(हवा चलने की आवाज़) (वस्तुओं के बजने की आवाज़)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(crying softly)
(धीरे-धीरे रोते हुए)
♪ Don't wish ♪
♪ कामना मत करो ♪
♪ Don't start ♪
♪ शुरू मत करो ♪
♪ Wishing only wounds the heart ♪
♪ कामना करने से दिल को और भी चोट पहुँचती है ♪
♪ There's a girl I know ♪
♪ मैं एक लड़की को जानता हूँ ♪
(softly): He loves her so.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): वह उससे बहुत प्यार करता है।
♪ I'm not that ♪
♪ मैं वो नहीं हूँ ♪
♪ Girl. ♪
♪ लड़की। ♪
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
(fabric whooshes)
(कपड़े की सरसराहट)
(crickets chirping)
(झींगुरों की आवाज़)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Kiss me too fiercely ♪
♪ मुझे भी बहुत ज़ोर से चूम लो ♪
♪ Hold me too tight ♪
♪ मुझे कसकर पकड़ो ♪
♪ I need help believing ♪
♪ मुझे विश्वास करने में मदद चाहिए ♪
♪ You're with me tonight ♪
♪ आज रात तुम मेरे साथ हो ♪
♪ My wildest dreamings ♪
♪ मेरे सबसे बड़े सपने ♪
♪ Could not foresee ♪
♪ भविष्यवाणी नहीं कर सका ♪
♪ Lying beside you ♪
♪ तुम्हारे बगल में लेटना ♪
♪ With you wanting me ♪
♪ जब तुम मुझे चाहोगे ♪
♪ Just for this moment ♪
♪ बस इसी पल के लिए ♪
♪ As long as you're mine ♪
♪ जब तक तुम मेरी हो ♪
♪ I've lost all resistance ♪
♪ मैंने अपना सारा प्रतिरोध खो दिया है ♪
♪ And crossed some borderline ♪
♪ और कुछ सीमा रेखा पार कर ली ♪
♪ And if it turns out ♪
♪ और अगर ऐसा हुआ तो ♪
♪ It's over too fast ♪
♪ ये बहुत जल्दी खत्म हो गया ♪
♪ I'll make every last moment last ♪
♪ मैं हर आखिरी पल को यादगार बनाऊंगा ♪
♪ As long as you're mine ♪
♪ जब तक तुम मेरी हो ♪
You're beautiful.
आप खूबसूरत हैं।
(chuckles softly)
(हल्की सी हंसी)
You don't have to lie to me.
आपको मुझसे झूठ बोलने की जरूरत नहीं है।
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
It's not lying.
यह झूठ नहीं है।
It's...
इसका...
What is it?
यह क्या है?
It's looking at things another way.
यह चीजों को एक अलग नजरिए से देखने का तरीका है।
♪ Maybe I'm brainless ♪
♪ शायद मैं बेवकूफ हूँ ♪
♪ Maybe I'm wise ♪
♪ शायद मैं समझदार हूँ ♪
♪ But you've got me seeing ♪
♪ लेकिन तुमने मुझे देखने पर मजबूर कर दिया है ♪
♪ Through different eyes ♪
♪ अलग नज़रिए से ♪
♪ Somehow I've fallen ♪
♪ किसी तरह मैं गिर गया हूँ ♪
♪ Under your spell ♪
♪ तुम्हारे जादू में ♪
♪ And somehow I'm feeling ♪
♪ और मुझे किसी तरह ऐसा लग रहा है ♪
♪ It's up that I fell ♪
♪ मैं ऊपर की ओर गिर पड़ा ♪
♪ Every moment ♪
♪ हर पल ♪
♪ As long as you're mine ♪
♪ जब तक तुम मेरी हो ♪
♪ I'll wake up my body ♪
♪ मैं अपने शरीर को जगाऊँगा ♪
♪ And make up for lost time ♪
♪ और बीते हुए समय की भरपाई करो ♪
♪ Say there's no future ♪
♪ कहते हैं कि कोई भविष्य नहीं है ♪
♪ For us as a pair ♪
♪ हम दोनों के लिए ♪
♪ And though I may know ♪
♪ और भले ही मुझे पता हो ♪
♪ I don't care ♪
♪ मुझे परवाह नहीं ♪
♪ Just for this moment ♪
♪ बस इसी पल के लिए ♪
♪ As long as you're mine ♪
♪ जब तक तुम मेरी हो ♪
♪ Come be how you want to ♪
♪ जैसा चाहो वैसा बनो ♪
♪ And see how bright we shine ♪
♪ और देखो हम कितनी चमक बिखेरते हैं ♪
♪ Borrow the moonlight ♪
♪ चांदनी उधार लो ♪
♪ Until it is through ♪
♪ जब तक यह पूरा न हो जाए ♪
♪ And know I'll be here ♪
♪ और जान लो मैं यहीं रहूंगा ♪
♪ Holding you ♪
♪ तुम्हें थामे हुए ♪
♪ As long as you're mine. ♪
♪ जब तक तुम मेरी हो। ♪
(both chuckle)
(दोनों हंसते हैं)
-What is it? -It's just...
-यह क्या है? -यह बस...
For the first time, I feel Wicked.
पहली बार मुझे दुष्टता का एहसास हो रहा है।
(wind whistling softly)
(हवा की हल्की सीटी की आवाज)
(rumbling)
(गड़गड़ाहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(thunder rumbling)
(गरजने की आवाज)
(thunder pulsing to hand movements)
( हाथों की हरकतों के साथ गरज की आवाज)
(wind whooshing
हाथों की हरकतों के साथ हवा की सरसराहट)
(thunder cracks)
(बिजली कड़कती है)
(wind howling)
(तेज हवा की आवाज)
GUARD: Take cover!
रक्षक: छुप जाओ!
GUARD 2: Get inside! Get inside!
गार्ड 2: अंदर जाओ! अंदर जाओ!
(panicked chatter and screaming)
(घबराहट भरी बड़बड़ाहट और चीख-पुकार)
(wind continues howling)
(हवा लगातार तेज चल रही है)
(cyclone roaring)
(चक्रवात की गर्जना)
(panicked chatter and screaming)
(घबराहट भरी बड़बड़ाहट और चीख-पुकार)
Boq! Boq!
रुको!
Where are you?
आप कहां हैं?
Come on! Come on! Inside!
चलो! चलो! अंदर आओ!
-(yelps) -Stay calm.
(चीखते हुए) - शांत रहो।
Move! (grunts) Go!
हटो! (घुरघुराहट) जाओ!
Boq!
बगीचा!
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(thunder crashing)
(बिजली कड़कने की आवाज)
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
FIYERO: You can't go on living here.
फियेरो: आप यहां रहना जारी नहीं रख सकते।
-They'll find you. -I'll be all right.
-वे तुम्हें ढूंढ लेंगे। -मैं ठीक रहूंगा।
Listen.
सुनना।
My family has a castle in Kiamo Ko.
मेरे परिवार का कियामो को में एक महल है ।
-Never lived in it. -Where do you live?
-मैं इसमें कभी नहीं रहा। -आप कहाँ रहते हैं?
In the other castle.
दूसरे किले में।
(chuckles): Okay.
(हंसते हुए): ठीक है।
-Of course. -I mean, it's the perfect hideout.
-बिल्कुल। -मेरा मतलब है, यह छिपने के लिए एकदम सही जगह है।
There's tunnels, secret passageways.
यहां सुरंगें हैं, गुप्त रास्ते हैं।
You'll be safer there.
आप वहां ज्यादा सुरक्षित रहेंगे।
NESSAROSE (faintly): Boq!
नेसारोज़ (धीमी आवाज़ में): बोक!
-Where are you? -What?
-तुम कहाँ हो? -क्या?
Boq!
बगीचा!
What is it?
यह क्या है?
What's wrong?
क्या गलत?
-(cyclone roaring) -(thunder crashing)
(चक्रवात की गर्जना) (बिजली कड़कने की आवाज)
This isn't gonna make any sense, but...
यह बात शायद समझ में न आए , लेकिन...
There's a house.
वहाँ एक घर है।
And it's flying through the sky.
और यह आकाश में उड़ रहा है।
(Nessarose screaming)
(नेसारोज़ चीख रही है)
(breathing heavily)
(तेजी से सांस लेते हुए)
(screaming continues faintly)
(चीखने की आवाज़ धीमी-धीमी सुनाई देती रहती है)
-(screaming) -(house thuds)
(चीखने की आवाज़) (घर के गिरने की आवाज़)
-(breathing heavily) -Hey, hey, hey.
(तेजी से सांस लेते हुए) -हे, हे, हे।
My sister.
मेरी बहन।
-She's in danger. I have to get to her. -What?
-वह खतरे में है। मुझे उसके पास जाना होगा। -क्या?
-I'm coming with you. -No.
-मैं तुम्हारे साथ आ रहा हूँ। -नहीं।
It's too dangerous.
यह बहुत खतरनाक है।
Will we ever see each other again?
क्या हम कभी दोबारा मिलेंगे?
(breathes deeply)
(गहरी सांस लेता है)
Elphaba, we are going to be together always.
एल्फाबा, हम हमेशा साथ रहेंगे ।
You can see houses flying through the sky,
आप आसमान में उड़ते हुए घर देख सकते हैं ।
-but you can't see that? -(chuckles)
-लेकिन क्या आप इसे देख नहीं सकते? -(हंसते हुए)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(Fiyero sighs)
(फियेरो आह भरता है)
-(wind roaring) -(thunder crashing)
(तेज हवा का शोर) (बिजली कड़कने की आवाज)
-(leaves rustling) -(branches crackling)
(पत्तियों की सरसराहट) (शाखाओं के चटकने की आवाज़)
(wind howling)
(तेज हवा की आवाज)
(Fiyero grunting)
(फियेरो गुर्राता है)
(panting)
(हाँफते हुए)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
(thunder crashing)
(बिजली कड़कने की आवाज)
(birds chirping)
(पक्षियों का चहचहाना)
(wind whistling softly)
(हवा की हल्की सीटी की आवाज)
(faint chatter in distance)
(दूर से हल्की फुसफुसाहट सुनाई दे रही है)
(Toto barking)
(टोटो का भौंकना)
-MUNCHKIN: This way, dear. -GLINDA: Goodbye, Dorothy.
-मंचकिन: इधर आओ, प्रिय। -ग्लिंडा: अलविदा, डोरोथी।
Bye, Dodo.
अलविदा, डोडो।
It's just that one road the whole time.
पूरे रास्ते में बस एक ही सड़क है ।
(happy chatter)
(खुशी भरी बातचीत)
Take your time. Hurry up, darling.
आराम से करो। जल्दी करो, प्रिये।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(gasps softly)
(हल्की सी सांस लेते हुए)
(softly): Goodbye, Nessa.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): अलविदा, नेसा।
-ELPHABA: What a touching display of grief. -Oh, shiz.
-एल्फाबा: कितना मार्मिक शोक प्रदर्शन है! -ओह, शिट!
I scare you?
मैंने तुम्हे डराया?
I seem to have that effect on people.
ऐसा लगता है कि लोगों पर मेरा यही प्रभाव होता है।
I would appreciate a moment to say goodbye to my sister.
मुझे अपनी बहन को अलविदा कहने के लिए कुछ पल चाहिए ।
Alone.
अकेला।
Of course.
बिल्कुल।
Oh, Nessa.
ओह, नेसा।
Forgive me.
क्षमा चाहता हूँ।
Oh, Elphaba, don't blame yourself, please.
ओह, एल्फाबा, कृपया खुद को दोष मत दो।
It's dreadful, it is.
यह बेहद भयावह है, सचमुच।
I mean... to have a house fall on you...
मतलब... किसी के ऊपर घर गिर जाए तो...
But accidents will happen.
लेकिन दुर्घटनाएं तो होती ही रहती हैं।
And...
और...
You call that an accident?
क्या आप इसे दुर्घटना कहते हैं?
You think cyclones just appear out of the blue?
क्या आपको लगता है कि चक्रवात अचानक ही प्रकट हो जाते हैं ?
I don't know.
मुझें नहीं पता।
I never really thought about it...
मैंने इसके बारे में कभी सोचा ही नहीं था...
And how dare you send that mulish farm girl
और तुम्हारी हिम्मत कैसे हुई उस जिद्दी किसान लड़की को भेजने की?
off to see the Wizard,
जादूगर से मिलने जा रहा हूँ,
as if he could do anything to help?
जैसे कि वह मदद करने के लिए कुछ कर सकता हो?
She's lost. She's far from home.
वह खो गई है। वह अपने घर से बहुत दूर है।
She took a dead woman's shoes.
उसने एक मृत महिला के जूते उठा लिए।
I had to do something.
मुझे कुछ करना था।
I'm a public figure now. People expect me to...
मैं अब एक सार्वजनिक हस्ती हूँ। लोग मुझसे उम्मीद करते हैं कि...
Lie?
झूठ?
Be encouraging.
प्रोत्साहन देते रहें।
Those shoes are all I have left of my sister.
ये जूते ही मेरी बहन की आखिरी निशानी हैं।
They weren't yours to give.
ये चीजें देने का अधिकार आपका नहीं था।
Yes, well, it seems a lot of us are taking things
हाँ, ऐसा लगता है कि हममें से बहुत से लोग चीजों को गंभीरता से ले रहे हैं।
that don't belong to us now, aren't we?
अब ये चीजें हमारी नहीं हैं, है ना?
No, you just wait a clock-tick.
नहीं, आपको बस एक पल इंतजार करना होगा।
It might be hard for you to comprehend
आपको इसे समझना मुश्किल हो सकता है।
that someone like him could choose someone like me,
कि उसके जैसा कोई व्यक्ति मेरे जैसे किसी को चुन सकता है,
but it's happened, and it's real.
लेकिन ऐसा हुआ है, और यह सच है।
And you can wave that ridiculous wand all you want.
और आप उस बेतुकी छड़ी को जितना चाहें उतना घुमा सकते हैं।
You can't change it.
आप इसे बदल नहीं सकते।
He never belonged to you.
वह कभी तुम्हारा नहीं था।
He doesn't love you.
वह तुमसे प्यार नहीं करता।
He never did.
उन्होंने ऐसा कभी नहीं किया।
He loves me.
वह मुझसे प्यार करता है।
Oh, my...
अरे बाप रे...
Feel better?
बेहतर महसूस करना?
I do.
मैं करता हूं।
Good.
अच्छा।
(yelps)
(चीखता है)
(scoffs)
(हंसते हुए)
Me, too.
मैं भी।
(grunts) Are you crazy?
(घुरघुराहट के साथ) क्या तुम पागल हो?
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
Excuse me. What do you think you're doing?
माफ कीजिए। आप ये क्या कर रहे हैं?
(yelps) Come on! Come on! Bring it!
(चीखते हुए) चलो! चलो! शुरू करो!
ELPHABA: Get back!
एल्फाबा: पीछे हटो!
-(pants) -(grunts)
(हांफते हुए) (घुरघुराहट की आवाज)
(grunts angrily)
(गुस्से से गुर्राता है)
Get-- Oh! Oh!
अरे! अरे!
(grunts fiercely) Let's go!
(जोर से गुर्राते हुए) चलो चलें!
-(Elphaba cackling) -(Glinda grunts)
(एल्फाबा खिलखिलाती है) (ग्लिंडा गुर्राती है)
You...
आप...
(mimics cackling)
(हंसने की नकल करते हुए)
Please.
कृपया।
Where'd you get that?
यह तुम्हें कहाँ से मिला?
(wand whooshing)
(जादू की छड़ी की सरसराहट)
What are you doing?
आप क्या कर रहे हो?
(strains)
(स्ट्रेन)
(grunts)
(घुरघुराहट)
Come on. Let's go, greenie!
चलो, चलते हैं, ग्रीनी!
Use your hands!
अपने हाथों का उपयोग करें!
(both shouting)
(दोनों चिल्ला रहे हैं)
-Come on! -(grunting)
चलो! (घुरघुराहट करते हुए)
-Bring it on! -You're out of your mind!
आओ मैदान में! तुम पागल हो गए हो!
-Get off of me! -No!
-मुझसे दूर हटो! -नहीं!
-GUARD: Attention! -(both grunting)
- रक्षक: सावधान! (दोनों गुर्राते हैं)
-Halt in the name of the Wizard! -GLINDA: Oh, come on!
-जादूगर के नाम पर रुको ! -ग्लिंडा: अरे, रहने दो!
-ELPHABA: Off of me! -GLINDA: Ow! Ow!
-एल्फाबा: मुझसे दूर हटो! -ग्लिंडा: आह! आह!
GLINDA: No, no, no, no. I almost had her.
ग्लिंडा: नहीं, नहीं, नहीं, नहीं। मैं लगभग उसे पकड़ ही चुकी थी।
-I almost had her. -(guard grunts)
-मैं लगभग उसे पकड़ ही चुका था। (गार्ड गुर्राता है)
I almost had her.
मैं लगभग उसे पकड़ ही चुका था।
-Easy. -(grunts)
-आसान है। (घुरघुराहट की आवाज़)
Sorry it took us so long to get here, Your Goodness.
हमें यहां आने में इतनी देर लगने के लिए क्षमा करें , महोदय।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
You were a part of this?
क्या आप भी इसमें शामिल थे?
-Elphaba, no... -I can't believe
-एल्फाबा, नहीं... -मुझे विश्वास नहीं हो रहा
you would stoop so low as to use my sister's death
तुम मेरी बहन की मौत का इस्तेमाल करके इतनी नीच हरकत करोगे।
to capture me.
मुझे पकड़ने के लिए।
I never meant to take it this far. I...
मेरा इरादा इसे इतना आगे ले जाने का कभी नहीं था। मैं...
-Let the green girl go. -(monkeys screeching)
-हरी लड़की को जाने दो। (बंदरों की चीखें)
Else explain to all Oz how the Wizard's guards
अन्यथा, ओज़ के सभी लोगों को समझाओ कि जादूगर के रक्षक कैसे...
watched while Glinda the Good was slain.
ग्लिंडा द गुड की हत्या होते हुए उसने सब कुछ देखा ।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(monkey squawks)
(बंदर की चीख)
(monkeys chattering)
(बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
-Elphaba, go. -No. Not without you.
-एल्फाबा, जाओ। -नहीं। तुम्हारे बिना नहीं।
Go!
जाना!
Go.
जाना।
I...
मैं...
Now.
अब।
Go.
जाना।
-Please, protect her. -(chatters)
-कृपया, उसकी रक्षा करो। (बड़बड़ाते हुए)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
(panting)
(हाँफते हुए)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(guards grunting)
(पहरेदार गुर्राते हैं)
(pained grunting)
(दर्द भरी कराह)
No! You're hurting him! Stop it now!
नहीं! तुम उसे चोट पहुँचा रहे हो! अभी रोक दो!
Stop it.
इसे रोक।
In the name of Goodness, stop!
भगवान के नाम पर, रुक जाओ!
(Fiyero panting)
(फियेरो हांफ रहा है)
Can't you see he wasn't going to harm me?
क्या तुम्हें नहीं दिख रहा कि वह मुझे नुकसान नहीं पहुँचाने वाला था?
He just...
वह बस...
He loves her.
वह उससे प्यार करता है।
Glinda, I am so sorry.
ग्लिंडा, मुझे बहुत खेद है।
-(whimpers) -Take him out to that field.
(सिसकते हुए) -उसे उस खेत में ले जाओ।
What? No, please.
क्या? नहीं, कृपया।
Put him up on those poles till he tells us
उसे तब तक उन खंभों पर लटकाए रखो जब तक वह हमें बता न दे।
-where the Witch went. -You're hurting him. No.
-चुड़ैल कहाँ गई? -तुम उसे चोट पहुँचा रहे हो। नहीं।
Fiyero! No! Please! Let go of me!
फ़ियेरो! नहीं! कृपया! मुझे छोड़ दो!
Fiyero! Fiyero!
फियेरो! फियेरो!
-(whooshing) -(monkeys screeching)
(तेज़ हवा की आवाज़) (बंदरों की चीख)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(whooshing)
(तेज़ हवा की आवाज़)
(chiming and crackling)
(घंटी बजने और चटकने की आवाज़)
♪ "Eleka nahmen nahmen ♪
♪ "एलेका ने लिया ♪
♪ "Ah tum ah tum eleka nahmen ♪
♪ "आह तुम आह तुम एलेका कामेन ♪
♪ Ah tum ah tum eleka nahmen" ♪
♪आह तुम आह तुम एलेका कामेन" ♪
♪ Let his flesh not be torn ♪
♪ उसके शरीर को नोचा न जाए ♪
-♪ Let his blood leave no stain ♪ -(grunts)
-♪ उसके खून का कोई दाग न लगे ♪ -(घुरघुराहट)
♪ Though they beat him, let him feel no pain ♪
♪ चाहे वे उसे पीटें, उसे दर्द न महसूस होने दें ♪
♪ Let his bones never break ♪
♪ उसकी हड्डियाँ कभी न टूटें ♪
♪ And however they try to destroy him ♪
♪ और चाहे वे उसे नष्ट करने की कितनी भी कोशिश करें ♪
-♪ Let him never die ♪ -(grunting)
-♪ उसकी कभी मृत्यु न हो ♪ -(घुरघुराहट)
♪ Let him never die ♪
♪ उसकी मृत्यु कभी न हो ♪
♪ "Eleka nahmen nahmen ♪
♪ "एलेका ने लिया ♪
♪ "Ah tum ah tum eleka nahmen ♪
♪ "आह तुम आह तुम एलेका कामेन ♪
♪ "Ah tum ah tum eleka ♪
♪ "Ah tum ah tum eleka ♪
-♪ Eleka" ♪ -(grunts)
-♪ एलेका" ♪ -(ग्राउंड)
What good is this chanting?
इस मंत्रोच्चारण से क्या लाभ है?
I don't even know what I'm reading.
मुझे तो यह भी नहीं पता कि मैं क्या पढ़ रहा हूँ।
♪ I don't even know what trick I ought to try ♪
♪ मुझे तो यह भी नहीं पता कि मुझे कौन सी तरकीब आजमानी चाहिए ♪
-(pained shout) -Fiyero, where are you?
(दर्द भरी चीख) -फियेरो, तुम कहाँ हो?
♪ Already dead or bleeding? ♪
♪ क्या पहले से ही मर चुके हैं या खून बह रहा है? ♪
♪ One more disaster I can add ♪
♪ एक और आपदा जिसे मैं जोड़ सकता हूँ ♪
-♪ To my generous ♪ -(rumbling)
-♪ मेरे उदार के लिए ♪ -(गड़गड़ाहट)
♪ Supply? ♪
♪ आपूर्ति? ♪
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
♪ No good deed goes unpunished ♪
♪ कोई भी अच्छा कर्म बिना दंड के नहीं रहता ♪
♪ No act of charity goes unresented ♪
♪ दान का कोई भी कार्य बिना विरोध के नहीं रहता ♪
♪ No good deed goes unpunished ♪
♪ कोई भी अच्छा कर्म बिना दंड के नहीं रहता ♪
♪ That's my new creed ♪
♪ यही मेरा नया सिद्धांत है ♪
♪ My road of good intentions led ♪
♪ मेरी नेक इरादों की राह ने मुझे आगे बढ़ाया ♪
♪ Where such roads always lead ♪
♪ जहाँ ऐसे रास्ते हमेशा ले जाते हैं ♪
♪ No good deed ♪
♪ कोई अच्छा काम नहीं ♪
♪ Goes unpunished ♪
♪ बिना किसी सजा के बच जाता है ♪
Nessa?
इसमें?
Dr. Dillamond.
डॉ. डिलमंड।
♪ Fiyero ♪
♪ फियेरो ♪
♪ One question haunts and hurts too much ♪
♪ एक सवाल मन में बार-बार आता है और बहुत दर्द देता है ♪
♪ Too much to mention ♪
♪ उल्लेख करने के लिए बहुत कुछ है ♪
♪ Was I really seeking good ♪
♪ क्या मैं सचमुच अच्छाई की तलाश कर रहा था ♪
♪ Or just seeking attention? ♪
♪ या फिर सिर्फ ध्यान आकर्षित करने की कोशिश? ♪
♪ Is that all good deeds are ♪
♪ क्या सभी अच्छे कर्म यही हैं ♪
♪ When looked at with an ice-cold eye? ♪
♪ जब किसी को बर्फीली निगाहों से देखा जाए? ♪
♪ If that's all good deeds are ♪
♪ अगर अच्छे कर्मों का यही सार है ♪
♪ Maybe that's the reason why ♪
♪ शायद यही कारण है ♪
♪ No good deed goes unpunished ♪
♪ कोई भी अच्छा कर्म बिना दंड के नहीं रहता ♪
♪ All helpful urges should be circumvented ♪
♪ सभी सहायक इच्छाओं को दरकिनार कर देना चाहिए ♪
♪ No good deed goes unpunished ♪
♪ कोई भी अच्छा कर्म बिना दंड के नहीं रहता ♪
♪ Sure, I meant well ♪
♪ हाँ, मेरा इरादा अच्छा था ♪
♪ Well, look at what well-meant did ♪
♪ देखो, नेक इरादे का क्या नतीजा निकला ♪
All right, enough! So be it!
ठीक है, बस बहुत हो गया! ऐसा ही हो!
So be it, then.
तो ठीक है।
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
Let all Oz be agreed.
ऑस्ट्रेलिया के सभी लोग इस बात से सहमत हों।
I'm Wicked.
मैं दुष्ट हूँ।
♪ Through and through ♪
♪ पूरी तरह से ♪
♪ And since I can't succeed, Fiyero, saving you ♪
♪ और चूंकि मैं तुम्हें बचाने में सफल नहीं हो सकता, फियेरो ♪
♪ I promise no good deed ♪
♪ मैं कोई अच्छा काम करने का वादा नहीं करता ♪
-♪ Will I attempt to do again ♪ -(thunder crashing)
-♪ क्या मैं दोबारा कोशिश करूँगा ♪ -(बिजली कड़कने की आवाज)
♪ Ever again ♪
♪ फिर कभी नहीं ♪
♪ No good deed will I do ♪
♪ मैं कोई अच्छा काम नहीं करूँगा ♪
♪ Again. ♪
♪ पुनः। ♪
(jaunty piano music playing)
(सुखद पियानो संगीत बज रहा है)
(door opens)
(दरवाजा खुलता है)
You have visitors.
आपके यहाँ मेहमान आए हुए हैं।
A girl from the land of Kansas
कैनसस की धरती से एक लड़की
and three friends she picked up along the way.
और रास्ते में उसे तीन दोस्त मिल गए।
A man made of tin, another made of straw
एक आदमी टिन का बना था, दूसरा भूसे का।
and a very nervous lion.
और एक बहुत घबराया हुआ शेर।
They all want something they don't have, of course.
वे सभी कुछ ऐसा चाहते हैं जो उनके पास नहीं है, बिल्कुल।
I'm not seeing anybody.
मैं किसी के साथ रिलेशनशिप में नहीं हूं।
But these are visitors we can use.
लेकिन ये ऐसे आगंतुक हैं जिनका हम उपयोग कर सकते हैं।
(door creaking)
(दरवाजे की चरमराहट)
(whimpers)
(सिसकते हुए)
(The Lion gasps, whimpers)
(शेर हांफता है, कराहता है)
(gears rattling)
(गियरों की खड़खड़ाहट)
Bring me the broomstick
मुझे झाड़ू ला दो
(deep, grating voice): of the Wicked Witch of the West...
(गहरी, कर्कश आवाज): पश्चिम की दुष्ट चुड़ैल के बारे में...
(The Lion whimpers)
(शेर कराहता है)
...so I have proof that she's dead.
...तो मेरे पास इस बात का सबूत है कि वह मर चुकी है।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(breathes deeply)
(गहरी सांस लेता है)
-OZIANS: ♪ Go and hunt her ♪ -(angry clamoring)
-ओज़ियंस: ♪ जाओ और उसका शिकार करो ♪ -(गुस्से में चिल्लाना)
♪ And find her and kill her ♪
♪ और उसे ढूंढकर मार डालो ♪
(angry clamoring continues)
(गुस्से भरी चीख-पुकार जारी है)
♪ Go and hunt her ♪
♪ जाओ और उसका शिकार करो ♪
♪ And find her and kill her ♪
♪ और उसे ढूंढकर मार डालो ♪
(chanting): Kill her! Kill her! Kill her!
(नारे लगाते हुए): उसे मार डालो! उसे मार डालो! उसे मार डालो!
♪ Go and hunt her ♪
♪ जाओ और उसका शिकार करो ♪
♪ And find her and kill her ♪
♪ और उसे ढूंढकर मार डालो ♪
(chanting): Melt her! Melt her!
(नारे लगाते हुए): उसे पिघला दो! उसे पिघला दो!
♪ Wickedness must be punished ♪
♪ दुष्टता को दंडित किया जाना चाहिए ♪
Kill her!
उसे मार!
♪ Evil effectively eliminated ♪
♪ बुराई का प्रभावी ढंग से खात्मा हो गया ♪
♪ Wickedness must be punished ♪
♪ दुष्टता को दंडित किया जाना चाहिए ♪
♪ Kill the Witch ♪
♪ चुड़ैल को मार डालो ♪
Kill her! Melt her!
उसे मार डालो! उसे पिघला दो!
♪ Melt the Witch ♪
♪ चुड़ैल को पिघला दो ♪
And this is more than just a service to the Wizard.
और यह जादूगर की सेवा से कहीं अधिक है।
I have a personal score to settle with Elph--
मुझे एल्फ से व्यक्तिगत हिसाब चुकता करना है--
with the Witch!
चुड़ैल के साथ!
-(cheering) -OZIAN: Yeah! Someone, kill her!
(खुशी मनाते हुए) -ओज़ियन: हाँ! कोई उसे मार डालो!
♪ It's due to her I'm made of tin ♪
♪ उसी की वजह से मैं टिन का बना हूँ ♪
♪ Her spell made this occur ♪
♪ उसके जादू से यह सब हुआ ♪
♪ So for once I'm glad I'm heartless ♪
♪ इसलिए पहली बार मुझे खुशी है कि मैं हृदयहीन हूँ ♪
♪ I'll be heartless killing her! ♪
♪ मैं उसे बेरहमी से मार डालूंगा! ♪
(cheering)
(जयकार)
And I'm not the only one.
और मैं अकेली नहीं हूँ।
(gasping)
(हाँफते हुए)
Tell them. Tell them what she did to you.
उन्हें बताओ। उन्हें बताओ कि उसने तुम्हारे साथ क्या किया।
How you were just a cub and she cub-napped you.
तुम तो बस एक शावक थे और उसने तुम्हें अगवा कर लिया था।
(Ozians gasping)
(ओज़ियन हांफ रहे हैं)
♪ You see, the Lion also ♪
♪ देखो, शेर भी ♪
-♪ Has a grievance to repay ♪ -(whimpering)
-♪ शिकायत का बदला चुकाना है ♪ -(सिसकते हुए)
♪ If she'd let him fight his own battles ♪
♪ अगर वह उसे अपनी लड़ाई खुद लड़ने देती ♪
♪ When he was young ♪
♪ जब वह जवान था ♪
♪ He wouldn't be a coward ♪
♪ वह कायर नहीं होगा ♪
-♪ Today ♪ -(clamoring)
-♪ आज ♪ -(शोर मचाते हुए)
-♪ Go and hunt her ♪ -(chanting): Go! Go!
-♪ जाओ और उसका शिकार करो ♪ -(मंत्रोच्चार करते हुए): जाओ! जाओ!
-♪ And find her and kill her ♪ -Go! Go! Go! Go!
-♪ और उसे ढूंढो और मार डालो ♪ -जाओ! जाओ! जाओ! जाओ!
-Kill her! Kill her!
-उसे मार डालो! उसे मार डालो!
-Kill her!
उसे मार डालो! उसे मार डालो! उसे मार डालो!
(breathing shakily)
(कांपती हुई सांसों के साथ)
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
(softly): Look.
(धीमी आवाज़ में): देखो।
♪ There's that beautiful girl ♪
♪ वो खूबसूरत लड़की है ♪
♪ With a beautiful life ♪
♪ एक खूबसूरत जीवन के साथ ♪
♪ Such a beautiful life ♪
♪ कितना खूबसूरत जीवन है ♪
♪ Built on lies ♪
♪ झूठ पर निर्मित ♪
♪ 'Cause all that's required ♪
♪ क्योंकि बस यही आवश्यक है ♪
♪ To live in a dream ♪
♪ सपने में जीना ♪
♪ Is endlessly closing your eyes ♪
♪ क्या यह अंतहीन रूप से अपनी आँखें बंद करना है ♪
♪ She spins such beautiful stories ♪
♪ वो कितनी खूबसूरत कहानियां सुनाती हैं ♪
♪ To sing her to sleep ♪
♪ उसे सुलाने के लिए गाना गाने के लिए ♪
♪ Full of magic and glory and love ♪
♪ जादू , महिमा और प्रेम से परिपूर्ण ♪
♪ She's the girl in the bubble ♪
♪ वो बुलबुले में रहने वाली लड़की है ♪
♪ The bright, shiny bubble ♪
♪ चमकीला, जगमगाता बुलबुला ♪
♪ Blissfully floating above ♪
♪ आनंद से ऊपर तैरते हुए ♪
♪ Ah, but the truth has a way ♪
♪ आह, लेकिन सच्चाई का अपना रास्ता होता है ♪
♪ Of seeping on in ♪
♪ रिसते हुए अंदर जाने का ♪
♪ Beneath the surface and sheen ♪
♪ सतह और चमक के नीचे ♪
♪ And blind as you try to be ♪
♪ और तुम चाहे जितनी भी अंधी बनने की कोशिश करो ♪
♪ Eventually ♪
♪ अंततः ♪
♪ It's hard to unsee what you've seen ♪
♪ जो देख लिया है उसे भुला पाना मुश्किल है ♪
♪ And so that beautiful girl ♪
♪ और वो खूबसूरत लड़की ♪
♪ With a beautiful life ♪
♪ एक खूबसूरत जीवन के साथ ♪
♪ Has a question that haunts her somehow ♪
♪ उसके मन में एक सवाल है जो उसे लगातार परेशान कर रहा है ♪
♪ If she comes down from the sky ♪
♪ अगर वह आसमान से नीचे आती है ♪
♪ Gives the real world a try ♪
♪ वास्तविक दुनिया को आजमाने का प्रयास करता है ♪
♪ Who in the world is she now? ♪
♪ आख़िर वो कौन है? ♪
♪ And though so much of her wishes ♪
♪ और हालाँकि उसकी बहुत सी इच्छाएँ ♪
♪ That she could float on ♪
♪ कि वह तैर सकती थी ♪
♪ And the beautiful lies never stop ♪
♪ और खूबसूरत झूठ कभी खत्म नहीं होते ♪
♪ For the girl in the bubble ♪
♪ बुलबुले में रहने वाली लड़की के लिए ♪
♪ The pink, shiny bubble ♪
♪ गुलाबी, चमकदार बुलबुला ♪
♪ It's time for her bubble to pop ♪
♪ अब उसके भ्रम के टूटने का समय आ गया है ♪
♪ For the popular girl ♪
♪ लोकप्रिय लड़की के लिए ♪
♪ High in the bubble ♪
♪ बुलबुले में ऊँचाई पर ♪
♪ Isn't it high time ♪
♪ क्या अब समय नहीं आ गया है ♪
♪ For her bubble ♪
♪ उसके बुलबुले के लिए ♪
♪ To pop? ♪
♪ पॉप करने के लिए? ♪
Madame, we have got to stop this.
महोदया, हमें इसे रोकना होगा।
It's gone too far.
बात हद से आगे बढ़ गई है।
I think Elphaba can take care of herself.
मुझे लगता है कि एल्फाबा अपना ख्याल खुद रख सकती है।
Madame.
महोदया।
Something has been troubling me.
मुझे कुछ बात परेशान कर रही है ।
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
About Nessa and that cyclone.
नेसा और उस चक्रवात के बारे में।
Sad.
दुखद।
I suppose it was just her time.
मुझे लगता है कि उसका समय आ गया था।
Was it?
यह था?
Was it? What did you do?
क्या ऐसा था? तुमने क्या किया?
Now, you listen to me, missy.
अब मेरी बात सुनो, मिस।
-(gasps) -You may be fooling the rest of Oz,
(हैरान होकर) -आप शायद बाकी ओज़ को बेवकूफ बना रहे हैं।
but you're not fooling me.
लेकिन आप मुझे बेवकूफ नहीं बना सकते।
-You wanted this from the beginning. -(gasps)
-तुम तो शुरू से यही चाहते थे। (हैरान होकर)
"Galinda."
"गलिंडा।"
And now you're getting what you wanted.
और अब आपको वही मिल रहा है जो आप चाहते थे।
-So just do what you do best. -No. No.
-तो बस वही करो जो तुम सबसे अच्छा करते हो। -नहीं। नहीं।
Smile.
मुस्कान।
-Wave. -(gasps, grunts)
-लहर। -(सांस फूलना, कराहना)
And shut up.
और चुप रहो।
(breathing shakily)
(कांपती हुई सांसों के साथ)
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
-I need your help. -(horse sputtering)
मुझे आपकी मदद चाहिए। (घोड़ा हांफ रहा था)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(neighs)
(हिनहिनाता है)
♪ Wickedness must be punished ♪
♪ दुष्टता को दंडित किया जाना चाहिए ♪
♪ Brave Witch Hunters, I would join you if I could ♪
♪ बहादुर चुड़ैल शिकारी, अगर मैं कर सकता तो मैं भी तुम्हारे साथ शामिल हो जाता ♪
♪ Because Wickedness must be punished ♪
♪ क्योंकि दुष्टता को दंडित किया जाना चाहिए ♪
♪ Punished, punished ♪
♪ दंडित, दंडित ♪
♪ For good ♪
♪ हमेशा के लिए ♪
-Monkeys! -(monkeys chattering)
-बंदर! -(बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
Find that Dorothy,
डोरोथी, उसे ढूंढो।
and bring back my sister's shoes!
और मेरी बहन के जूते वापस ले आओ!
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(neighs)
(हिनहिनाता है)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
(Dorothy screaming)
(डोरोथी चीख रही है)
(neighs)
(हिनहिनाता है)
-ELPHABA: Oh, for Oz's sake, stop crying! -(Dorothy crying)
-एल्फाबा: अरे, ओज़ के लिए रोना बंद करो! (डोरोथी रो रही है)
I can't listen to it anymore.
मैं इसे अब और नहीं सुन सकता।
You want to get home and see your Aunt what's-her-name again?
क्या तुम घर जाकर अपनी उस चाची से दोबारा मिलना चाहते हो जिसका नाम मुझे याद नहीं आ रहा?
-DOROTHY: Please stop. -Then get those shoes
-डोरोथी: कृपया रुक जाओ। -तो फिर वो जूते ले आओ।
-off your feet! -I'm so sorry.
-अपने पैरों से हट जाओ! -मुझे बहुत खेद है।
-(grunts) -(Dorothy continues crying)
(घुरघुराहट की आवाज़) (डोरोथी रोती रहती है)
-DOROTHY: I want to go home. -(monkeys chattering)
-डोरोथी: मैं घर जाना चाहती हूँ। (बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
GLINDA: They're coming for you.
ग्लिंडा: वे तुम्हारे लिए आ रहे हैं।
Let the little girl go.
उस छोटी बच्ची को जाने दो।
Go away.
दूर जाओ।
Elphaba, you can't go on like this.
एल्फाबा, तुम इस तरह से नहीं चल सकती।
I can do whatever I want. Haven't you heard?
मैं जो चाहूँ वो कर सकता हूँ। क्या तुमने सुना नहीं?
I'm the Wicked Witch of the West.
मैं पश्चिम की दुष्ट चुड़ैल हूँ ।
Chistery, at last.
अंततः चिस्टरी।
What took you so long?
आपको इतनी देर क्यों हुई?
What is this?
यह क्या है?
Elphie, what is that?
एल्फी, यह क्या है?
It's Fiyero, isn't it?
ये फियेरो है, है ना?
Is he...
क्या वह है...
We've seen his face for the last time.
हमने उसका चेहरा आखिरी बार देख लिया है।
Oh, no. (gasps)
ओह, नहीं। (हैरान होकर)
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
(Glinda continues crying)
(ग्लिंडा रोती रहती है)
You're right.
आप ठीक कह रहे हैं।
It's time.
यह समय है।
I surrender.
मैं आत्मसमर्पण करता हूं।
What? Wait.
क्या? रुको।
(Glinda crying)
(ग्लिंडा रो रही है)
Elphaba, what are you doing?
एल्फाबा, तुम क्या कर रही हो?
Glinda, you can't be found here with me.
ग्लिंडा, तुम मेरे साथ यहां नहीं मिल सकती ।
-You must go. -Elphie, no. I...
-तुम्हें जाना होगा। -एल्फी, नहीं। मैं...
Please, you must now.
कृपया, आपको अब ऐसा करना होगा।
Fine.
अच्छा।
I'll go and I'll tell everyone the truth about you,
मैं जाकर सबको तुम्हारे बारे में सच बता दूंगा।
-that you're not who they say you are. -No, you can't.
-कि आप वो नहीं हैं जो लोग आपके बारे में कहते हैं। -नहीं, आप ऐसा नहीं कर सकते।
-(exasperated sigh) -They'll just turn against you.
(निराशा भरी आह) -वे तुम्हारे ही खिलाफ हो जाएंगे।
-Well, I don't care. -Well, I do.
-खैर, मुझे परवाह नहीं है। -खैर, मुझे परवाह है।
I need you to promise that you won't try to clear my name.
मुझे आपसे यह वादा चाहिए कि आप मेरा नाम साफ करने की कोशिश नहीं करेंगे।
No. What? Why would I do that? I'll tell them everything.
नहीं। क्या? मैं ऐसा क्यों करूँगा? मैं उन्हें सब कुछ बता दूँगा।
-Please. -No, I don't want you to do that. Please.
-कृपया। -नहीं, मैं नहीं चाहता कि आप ऐसा करें। कृपया।
I'll tell them you're not who they say you are.
मैं उन्हें बता दूंगा कि तुम वो नहीं हो जो वे तुम्हारे बारे में बता रहे हैं।
I just want you to just listen for a minute.
मैं चाहता हूं कि आप बस एक मिनट के लिए मेरी बात सुनें।
-Please, please just... -Just promise me!
-प्लीज़, प्लीज़ बस... -बस मुझसे वादा कर दो!
Why would you ask me to promise that?
आप मुझसे ऐसा वादा करने के लिए क्यों कह रहे हैं ?
Because they need someone to be Wicked
क्योंकि उन्हें किसी दुष्ट व्यक्ति की आवश्यकता है।
so that you can be Good.
ताकि तुम अच्छे बन सको।
(sobs)
(सिसकियाँ)
(voice breaking): ♪ I'm limited ♪
(आवाज लड़खड़ाते हुए): ♪ मैं सीमित हूँ ♪
Just look at me.
मुझे देखो।
Not with your eyes.
अपनी आँखों से नहीं।
With theirs.
उनके साथ।
♪ I'm limited ♪
♪ मेरी सीमाएं हैं ♪
♪ And just look at you ♪ (sobs softly)
♪ और तुम्हें देखो ♪ (धीरे-धीरे सिसकते हुए)
♪ You can do all I couldn't do ♪
♪ तुम वो सब कर सकते हो जो मैं नहीं कर सकता ♪
♪ Glinda ♪
♪ ग्लिंडा ♪
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Here. Take it.
लो। इसे ले लो।
-What? Elphie... -Go on.
-क्या? एल्फी... -आगे बोलो।
Take it.
इसे लें।
But you know I... I can't read this. I...
लेकिन आप जानते हैं कि मैं... मैं इसे पढ़ नहीं सकता। मैं...
Well, you'll have to learn.
खैर, आपको सीखना ही पड़ेगा।
We can't let "Good" be just a word.
हम "अच्छा" को सिर्फ एक शब्द बनकर नहीं रहने दे सकते ।
It has to mean something.
इसका कुछ न कुछ मतलब तो जरूर होगा।
It has to change things.
इससे बदलाव आना ही चाहिए।
♪ Because now it's up to you ♪
♪ क्योंकि अब यह आप पर निर्भर है ♪
(whispers): For both of us.
(फुसफुसाते हुए): हम दोनों के लिए।
♪ Now it's up to you ♪
♪ अब यह आप पर निर्भर है ♪
-(sobs softly) -You know, um...
(धीरे-धीरे सिसकते हुए) - तुम्हें पता है, उम...
You're the only friend I ever had.
तुम ही मेरे इकलौते दोस्त हो ।
(chuckles softly)
(हल्की सी हंसी)
And I've had so many friends.
और मेरे बहुत सारे दोस्त रहे हैं।
(both laugh)
(दोनों हंसते हैं)
But only one that mattered.
लेकिन केवल एक ही महत्वपूर्ण था।
♪ I've heard it said ♪
♪ मैंने सुना है कि ऐसा कहा जाता है ♪
♪ That people come into our lives for a reason ♪
♪ लोग किसी न किसी कारण से हमारे जीवन में आते हैं ♪
♪ Bringing something we must learn ♪
♪ कुछ ऐसा लाना जो हमें सीखना चाहिए ♪
♪ And we are led ♪
♪ और हमें आगे बढ़ाया जाता है ♪
♪ To those who help us most to grow ♪
♪ उन लोगों के लिए जो हमें आगे बढ़ने में सबसे ज्यादा मदद करते हैं ♪
♪ If we let them ♪
♪ अगर हम उन्हें ऐसा करने दें ♪
♪ And we help them in return ♪
♪ और बदले में हम उनकी मदद करते हैं ♪
♪ Well, I don't know if I believe that's true ♪
♪ खैर, मुझे नहीं पता कि मैं इस बात को सच मानता हूँ या नहीं ♪
♪ But I know I'm who I am today ♪
♪ लेकिन मुझे पता है कि मैं आज जो हूँ वही हूँ ♪
♪ Because I knew you ♪
♪ क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ Like a comet pulled from orbit ♪
♪ जैसे कोई धूमकेतु अपनी कक्षा से बाहर निकल गया हो ♪
♪ As it passes a sun ♪
♪ जैसे ही यह सूर्य के पास से गुजरता है ♪
♪ Like a stream that meets a boulder ♪
♪ जैसे कोई धारा किसी चट्टान से टकराती है ♪
♪ Halfway through the wood ♪
♪ जंगल के बीचोंबीच ♪
♪ Who can say if I've been changed for the better? ♪
♪ कौन कह सकता है कि मुझमें सुधार हुआ है या नहीं? ♪
♪ But because I knew you ♪
♪ लेकिन क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
(chuckles, sniffles)
(हंसते हुए, नाक पोंछते हुए)
♪ I have been changed ♪
♪ मैं बदल गया हूँ ♪
♪ For good ♪
♪ हमेशा के लिए ♪
♪ It well may be ♪
♪ ऐसा हो सकता है ♪
♪ That we will never meet again ♪
♪ कि हम फिर कभी नहीं मिलेंगे ♪
♪ In this lifetime ♪
♪ इस जीवनकाल में ♪
♪ So let me say before we part ♪
♪ बिछड़ने से पहले मैं कुछ कहना चाहता हूँ ♪
♪ So much of me is made ♪
♪ मेरा बहुत कुछ हिस्सा बना है ♪
♪ Of what I learned from you ♪
♪ जो मैंने तुमसे सीखा ♪
♪ You'll be with me ♪
♪ तुम मेरे साथ रहोगे ♪
♪ Like a handprint on my heart ♪
♪ मेरे दिल पर एक हाथ के निशान की तरह ♪
♪ And now whatever way our stories end ♪
♪ और अब चाहे हमारी कहानियों का अंत किसी भी तरह से हो ♪
♪ I know you have rewritten mine ♪
♪ मुझे पता है तुमने मेरा लिखा हुआ फिर से लिख दिया है ♪
♪ By being my friend ♪
♪ मेरे दोस्त बनकर ♪
♪ Like a ship blown from its mooring ♪
♪ जैसे कोई जहाज अपनी लंगरगाह से बह गया हो ♪
♪ By a wind off the sea ♪
♪ समुद्र से आती हवा से ♪
♪ Like a seed dropped by a sky bird ♪
♪ जैसे आकाश में उड़ने वाले पक्षी द्वारा गिराया गया बीज ♪
♪ In a distant wood ♪
♪ दूर जंगल में ♪
♪ Who can say if I've been changed for the better? ♪
♪ कौन कह सकता है कि मुझमें सुधार हुआ है या नहीं? ♪
♪ But because I knew you ♪
♪ लेकिन क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ Because I knew you ♪
♪ क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ I have been changed for good ♪
♪ मैं अच्छे के लिए बदल गया हूँ ♪
ELPHABA: ♪ And just to clear the air ♪
एल्फाबा: ♪ और बस गलतफहमी दूर करने के लिए ♪
♪ I ask forgiveness ♪
♪ मैं क्षमा मांगता हूँ ♪
♪ For the things I've done you blame me for ♪
♪ मैंने जो कुछ किया है, उसके लिए तुम मुझे दोषी ठहराते हो ♪
♪ But then I guess ♪
♪ लेकिन फिर मुझे लगता है ♪
♪ We know there's blame to share ♪
♪ हमें पता है कि इसमें सबकी गलती है ♪
♪ And none of it seems to matter anymore ♪
♪ और अब इनमें से किसी बात का कोई महत्व नहीं रह गया है ♪
♪ Like a comet pulled from orbit ♪
♪ जैसे कोई धूमकेतु अपनी कक्षा से बाहर निकल गया हो ♪
♪ Like a ship blown from its mooring ♪
♪ जैसे कोई जहाज अपनी लंगरगाह से बह गया हो ♪
♪ As it passes a sun ♪
♪ जैसे ही यह सूर्य के पास से गुजरता है ♪
♪ By a wind off the sea ♪
♪ समुद्र से आती हवा से ♪
♪ Like a stream that meets a boulder ♪
♪ जैसे कोई धारा किसी चट्टान से टकराती है ♪
♪ Like a seed dropped by a bird ♪
♪ जैसे चिड़िया द्वारा गिराया गया बीज ♪
-♪ Halfway through the wood ♪ -♪ In the wood ♪
-♪ जंगल के बीचोंबीच ♪ -♪ जंगल में ♪
♪ Who can say ♪
♪ कौन कह सकता है ♪
♪ If I've been changed for the better? ♪
♪ क्या मुझमें बेहतर बदलाव आया है ? ♪
♪ I do believe I have been ♪
♪ मुझे यकीन है कि मैं रहा हूँ ♪
♪ Changed for the better ♪
♪ बेहतर के लिए बदल गया ♪
(Glinda chuckles softly)
(ग्लिंडा धीरे से हंसती है)
♪ And because I knew you ♪
♪ और क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ Because I knew you ♪
♪ क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ I have been changed ♪
♪ मैं बदल गया हूँ ♪
(chuckles, sniffles)
(हंसते हुए, नाक पोंछते हुए)
♪ For good. ♪
♪ हमेशा के लिए। ♪
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
Come on. Come on, quick.
चलो, जल्दी चलो।
No one can know you were here.
किसी को पता नहीं चलना चाहिए कि आप यहां थे।
-(hushed): You stay here. -What?
(धीमी आवाज़ में): तुम यहीं रहो। -क्या?
Everything's gonna be fine.
सब कुछ अच्छा होगा।
I love you.
मुझे तुमसे प्यार है।
I love you, too.
मैं भी आपसे प्यार करता हूँ।
(both crying)
(दोनों रो रहे हैं)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(both sniffle)
(दोनों सिसकते हैं)
(footsteps departing)
(दूर जाते कदमों की आहट)
(distant rumbling)
(दूर से आती गड़गड़ाहट की आवाज)
-(distant clamoring) -(footsteps running)
(दूर से आती हुई कोलाहल की आवाज) (दौड़ते कदमों की आहट)
(monkey screeches)
(बंदर की चीख)
-(distant clattering) -(monkeys screeching)
(दूर से आती खड़खड़ाहट की आवाज) (बंदरों की चीख)
(distant shouting)
(दूर से आती हुई चीखें)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(door opens)
(दरवाजा खुलता है)
-(Toto barking) -(monkeys screeching)
(टोटो का भौंकना) (बंदरों की चीख)
-(sobbing softly) -(banging, clamoring)
(धीरे-धीरे सिसकते हुए) (जोर-जोर से आवाज़ें निकालते हुए, शोर मचाते हुए)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
OZIANS: ♪ And Goodness knows ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ और ईश्वर ही जानता है ♪
♪ The Wicked's lives are lonely ♪
♪ दुष्टों का जीवन एकाकी होता है ♪
(sobs softly)
(धीरे-धीरे सिसकते हुए)
(breathing shakily)
(कांपती हुई सांसों के साथ)
♪ Goodness knows ♪
♪ ईश्वर ही जाने ♪
♪ The Wicked die alone. ♪
♪ दुष्ट अकेले ही मरते हैं। ♪
(water splashing)
(पानी के छींटे)
(Elphaba screaming)
(एल्फाबा चीख रही है)
(screaming fades)
(चीखने की आवाज़ धीमी हो जाती है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(sobbing softly)
(धीरे-धीरे सिसकते हुए)
Oh, Elphie.
ओह, एल्फी।
(crying)
(रोते हुए)
(Chistery grunting softly)
(चिस्टरी धीरे से गुर्राता है)
Miss Glinda.
मिस ग्लिंडा।
(gasps)
(हैरानी से)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(grunts softly)
(धीमी सी गुर्राहट)
(monkeys screeching)
(बंदरों की चीखें)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(door opens)
(दरवाजा खुलता है)
She's dead.
वह मर चुकी है।
-Do you have her broomstick? -No.
-क्या आपके पास उसकी झाड़ू है? -नहीं।
But I do have something else that belonged to her.
लेकिन मेरे पास उसकी एक और चीज भी है।
It was a keepsake.
यह एक यादगार वस्तु थी।
She told me herself.
उसने मुझे खुद बताया।
It belonged to her mother.
यह उसकी मां का था।
(sighs)
(आह भरते हुए)
This belonged to...
यह ... का था।
...her mother?
...उसकी माँ?
(mutters softly)
(धीमी आवाज़ में बुदबुदाता है)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(model train bell clanging)
(मॉडल ट्रेन की घंटी बजने की आवाज़)
(model train chugging)
(मॉडल ट्रेन की आवाज)
(whistle blowing)
(सीटी बजाना)
(giggling)
(हंसते हुए)
-(chuckles) -(gasps)
(हैरान होकर)
GLINDA: So Elphaba was yours all along.
ग्लिंडा: तो एल्फाबा तो हमेशा से तुम्हारी ही थी।
That's why she had such powers.
इसीलिए उसके पास इतनी शक्तियां थीं।
She was a child of both worlds.
वह दोनों दुनियाओं की संतान थी।
Oh, my Lord.
हे प्रभु!
(breathes shakily)
(कांपती हुई सांसें)
What have I done?
मैने क्या कि?
You have caused great harm.
आपने बहुत बड़ा नुकसान पहुंचाया है।
Which is why you will be leaving Oz.
इसीलिए आप ऑस्ट्रेलिया छोड़ रहे हैं।
Today.
आज।
Did you hear what I said?
क्या तुमने मेरी बात सुनी?
And what... what will I tell people?
और मैं लोगों को क्या बताऊँगा?
Make something up.
कुछ अच्छा बनाओ।
You're good at that.
आप इसमें माहिर हैं।
(gears rattling and clanking)
(गियरों की खड़खड़ाहट और झनझनाहट)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(gear clangs)
(गियर की खड़खड़ाहट)
(tapping on glass)
(कांच पर थपथपाते हुए)
Excuse me.
माफ़ करें।
Hello.
नमस्ते।
What? What do you want?
क्या? तुम क्या चाहते हो?
Look out your window.
अपनी खिड़की से बाहर देखो।
Come on. (chuckles)
चलो ना। (हंसते हुए)
You don't want to miss this.
आप इसे बिल्कुल भी मिस नहीं करना चाहेंगे।
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
DOROTHY: Excuse me, please. Don't leave without us.
डोरोथी: क्षमा कीजिए, कृपया। हमारे बिना मत जाइए।
Please. I-I want to go home.
कृपया। मैं घर जाना चाहता हूँ।
Ugh, I swear it never ends with that girl.
उफ़, कसम से, उस लड़की के साथ ये सब कभी खत्म नहीं होता।
(Ozians exclaiming, chattering excitedly)
(ओज़ियन लोग उत्साह से चिल्लाते और बातें करते हैं)
The Wizard is taking a permanent leave of absence.
जादूगर स्थायी अवकाश पर जा रहा है।
Not a rumor, a fact.
यह अफवाह नहीं, बल्कि एक तथ्य है।
The kind that is true.
जो सच हो।
Glinda, dear.
ग्लिंडा, प्रिय।
Can you not find it in your heart t-to forgive me?
क्या आप मुझे माफ नहीं कर सकते ?
As Oz is my witness,
ओज़ इसका गवाह है,
I can see now how truly good you are.
अब मुझे समझ आ रहा है कि आप वास्तव में कितने अच्छे हैं।
Actually, I'm not.
दरअसल, मैं नहीं हूँ।
Not yet.
अभी तक नहीं।
But just think, Madame.
लेकिन जरा सोचिए, महोदया।
We have so many cages, and all recently vacated.
हमारे पास बहुत सारे पिंजरे हैं, और ये सभी हाल ही में खाली किए गए हैं।
You'll have your pick. (chuckles)
आपको चुनने का मौका मिलेगा। (हंसते हुए)
Although I can't imagine you'll hold up very well.
हालांकि मुझे नहीं लगता कि आप ज्यादा देर तक टिक पाएंगे।
I mean, my personal opinion is you do not have what it takes.
मेरा मतलब है, मेरी निजी राय यह है कि आपमें वह काबिलियत नहीं है।
I hope you prove me wrong.
मुझे उम्मीद है कि आप मुझे गलत साबित करेंगे।
I doubt you will.
मुझे संदेह है कि आप ऐसा करेंगे।
(monkeys chattering)
(बंदरों की चहचहाहट)
What are you doing? Let go of me! Let...
तुम क्या कर रहे हो? मुझे छोड़ दो! मुझे जाने दो...
-(screaming) -(monkeys screeching)
(चीखने की आवाज़) (बंदरों की चीख)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(wand ringing)
(छड़ी की झंकार)
OZIANS: ♪ Good news... ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ खुशखबरी... ♪
(excited chatter)
(उत्साहित बातचीत)
♪ She's dead ♪
♪ वह मर चुकी है ♪
♪ The Witch of the West is dead ♪
♪ पश्चिम की चुड़ैल मर गई ♪
-♪ The Wickedest Witch there ever was ♪ -(cheering)
-♪ सबसे दुष्ट चुड़ैल ♪ -(जयकार)
♪ The enemy of all of us here in Oz ♪
♪ ऑस्ट्रेलिया में हम सभी का दुश्मन ♪
♪ Is dead ♪
♪ मर गया ♪
♪ Good news ♪
♪ खुशखबरी ♪
♪ Good news. ♪
♪ खुशखबरी। ♪
(cheering continues)
(जयकार जारी है)
Whoo! Yep.
वाह! हाँ।
(chuckles)
(हंसते हुए)
Well, this has been fun.
वाह, यह तो मजेदार रहा।
As you can imagine, I have much to attend to
जैसा कि आप समझ सकते हैं, मुझे बहुत सारे काम निपटाने हैं।
with the Wizard's unexpected departure,
जादूगर के अचानक चले जाने से,
so if there are no further questions, I'm gonna go.
तो अगर और कोई सवाल नहीं हैं, तो मैं जा रहा हूँ।
MUNCHKIN: Glinda.
मंचकिन: ग्लिंडा।
Is it true you were her friend?
क्या यह सच है कि आप उसकी दोस्त थीं?
(muffled): What?
(धीमी आवाज़ में): क्या?
Sorry. One sec.
क्षमा करें। एक पल रुकिए।
(clears throat)
(गला साफ करते हुए)
(clearly): What?
(स्पष्ट रूप से): क्या?
Is it true you were her friend?
क्या यह सच है कि आप उसकी दोस्त थीं?
(Ozians gasping, murmuring)
(ओज़ियन हांफते और बुदबुदाते हैं)
Friend?
दोस्त?
Yes.
हाँ।
(Ozians gasping, murmuring)
(ओज़ियन हांफते और बुदबुदाते हैं)
I-I mean, I did know her.
मतलब, मैं उसे जानता था।
(murmuring continues)
(फुसफुसाहट जारी है)
That is...
वह है...
our paths did cross.
हमारे रास्ते अवश्य ही एक दूसरे से टकराए।
At school.
स्कूल में।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
Wait.
इंतज़ार।
I have something more to say.
मुझे अभी कुछ और कहना है।
(Ozians murmuring)
(ओज़ियन आपस में फुसफुसा रहे हैं)
Fellow Ozians...
प्रिय ओज़ियन...
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
All Ozians.
सभी ओज़ियन।
(birds squawking)
(पक्षियों की चहचहाहट)
-Yes, come out. -(animals chittering)
-हाँ, बाहर आओ। (जानवरों की चहचहाहट)
Wherever you are, come out.
आप जहां भी हों, बाहर आ जाइए।
(bird chirps)
(पक्षी चहचहाते हैं)
(grumbles)
(बड़बड़ाता है)
Friends.
दोस्त।
(squeaking)
(चू चू की आवाज)
Because I don't see any enemies here.
क्योंकि मुझे यहां कोई दुश्मन नजर नहीं आता ।
(mooing softly)
(धीमी आवाज़ में गाय की तरह रंभाना)
(chittering)
(चिटरिंग)
(chirping)
(चहचहाना)
We have been through a frightening time.
हम एक भयावह दौर से गुजरे हैं ।
And there will be other times
और ऐसे और भी मौके आएंगे।
and other things that frighten us.
और अन्य चीजें जो हमें डराती हैं।
But if you'll let me...
लेकिन अगर आप मुझे अनुमति दें तो...
...I'd like to try to help.
मैं मदद करने की कोशिश करना चाहूंगा।
To change things.
चीजों को बदलने के लिए।
I'd like to try to be Glinda the Good.
मैं ग्लिंडा द गुड बनने की कोशिश करना चाहूंगी ।
(Ozians cheering)
(ओज़ियन लोग जयकार कर रहे हैं)
(birds chirping)
(पक्षियों का चहचहाना)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(vocalizing softly)
(धीमी आवाज़ में बोलते हुए)
(faint cheering)
(हल्की-सी जयकार)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(knock)
(खटखटाना)
FIYERO: It worked.
फियेरो: यह काम कर गया।
They all think you're dead.
वे सब सोचते हैं कि तुम मर चुके हो।
Fiyero?
कितना?
See?
देखना?
Good as new.
नए की तरह अच्छा।
You saved my life.
आप मेरी जान बचाई।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
-You're beautiful. -(chuckles)
-तुम बहुत खूबसूरत हो। (हंसते हुए)
You don't have to lie to me.
आपको मुझसे झूठ बोलने की जरूरत नहीं है।
(both laugh)
(दोनों हंसते हैं)
It's not lying.
यह झूठ नहीं है।
It's... (sighs)
यह... (आह भरते हुए)
It's looking at things in another way.
यह चीजों को एक अलग नजरिए से देखने का तरीका है।
Time to go.
अब जाने का समय हो गया है।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
ELPHABA: I wish that Glinda could know we're alive.
एल्फाबा: काश ग्लिंडा को पता चल जाता कि हम जीवित हैं।
But I know she can't.
लेकिन मुझे पता है कि वह ऐसा नहीं कर सकती।
No one can ever know.
कोई भी कभी नहीं जान सकता।
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
(thunder rumbling softly)
(धीमी गड़गड़ाहट की आवाज)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
♪ Who can say ♪
♪ कौन कह सकता है ♪
♪ If I've been changed ♪
♪ अगर मैं बदल गया हूँ ♪
♪ For the better, but ♪
♪ बेहतर के लिए, लेकिन ♪
BOTH: ♪ Because I knew you ♪
दोनों: ♪ क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
OZIANS: ♪ No one mourns the Wicked ♪
ओज़ियंस: ♪ दुष्टों के लिए कोई शोक नहीं मनाता ♪
♪ Because I knew you ♪
♪ क्योंकि मैं तुम्हें जानता था ♪
♪ I have been changed ♪
♪ मैं बदल गया हूँ ♪
♪ No one mourns the Wicked ♪
♪ दुष्टों के लिए कोई शोक नहीं मनाता ♪
(whooshing)
(तेज़ हवा की आवाज़)
(wind whistling)
(हवा की सीटी)
♪ Wicked ♪
♪ दुष्ट ♪
♪ Wicked. ♪
♪ दुष्ट। ♪
(music ends)
(संगीत समाप्त)
♪ ♪
♪ ♪
(music fades)
(संगीत धीरे-धीरे बंद हो जाता है)